<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lemmata meditationum, or, The contents of a few religious meditations given as directive and incentive to that invaluable duty / by Philo-Jesus Philo-Carolus.</title>
            <author>Philo-Carolus, Philo-Jesus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41777</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31360635</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31360635</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47662)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1744:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lemmata meditationum, or, The contents of a few religious meditations given as directive and incentive to that invaluable duty / by Philo-Jesus Philo-Carolus.</title>
                  <author>Philo-Carolus, Philo-Jesus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[23], 177 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>To be sold by Joseph Wilde, Bookseller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [23].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, cropped, and tightly bound, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Lemmata</hi> MEDITATIONUM OR, The <hi>Contents</hi> of a few Religious <hi>MEDITATIONS.</hi> Given as Directive and Incentive to that invaluable DUTY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Philo-Jeſus Philo-Carolus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 11.148.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Mine eyes prevent the Night-watches, that I might meditate in thy word.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 139.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When I awake, I am ſtill with Thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN;</hi> To be ſold by <hi>Joſeph Wilde,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Caſtleſtreet.</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:3"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mich: De Laune</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto Patri, ae Domino, Dno <hi>Michaeli,</hi> Archiepiſcopo <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linienſi;</hi> nec non ſummo <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernie</hi> Cancellario è ſacris.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To my EXCELLENT MOTHER, <hi>Grace and joy in the Holy Ghoſt be multiplyed.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Deareſt Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Papers were long written for my own peculiar uſe, and laid abbout the ſhelves of my ſtudy; in a dreſs, whoſe hue they yet retain: and indeed ſo ſenſible I am, of the unfitneſs of ſuch Youth as mine, to appear in Print, that were I not under the Preſs my ſelf, I would not ſuffer my <hi>Soliloquy's,</hi> ever to come under it; and the rather,
<pb facs="tcp:110756:5"/>becauſe intending them pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my own ſervice in their draught, I expended my whole induſtry in getting affections, and neglected that accuracy in the contexture of my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, which otherwiſe I had taken. Renewing the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, is a Task, that I (a poor Day-labourer) can by no means ſet on; and ſith I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with thoſe, who think this worthy to be ſent abroad, a neceſſity is laid upon me to ſend it as 'tis. You know, I never affected taudry faſhions in my own Garb, nor indeed do I in my Books; and I have a ſatisfaction to my ſelf, in that thoſe judicious Chriſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:110756:5"/>who gat it out of my hands, eſteem it as clad (at the leaſt) decently. A very aged and learned Doctor, (an eminent Dignitary of this Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi>) whom I never yet ſaw, ſave once, and that but on an occaſion, which gave me no more than a half-hours Diſcourſe with him,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>W.S.</hi>
               </note> hath in an affectionate Letter to me theſe very words: <q>In theſe Papers I now with many thanks ſend you, you have made choice of acceptable words, choice arguments, and ſuperexcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently expreſſed; no language ever better. You have ſpoken your own thoughts by Gods words; ſo that no enemy,
<pb facs="tcp:110756:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>not the Devil himſelf, can ſay, but that you have ſaid as well as may be, though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Theology is cultivated in moſt of its parts, beyond what is found among Foreigners; yet, I think, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> outgo us in Devotionary Books. We are forced to Engliſh and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome of theirs, to make them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Thomas de Kem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, Bellarmine, Parſons,</hi> &amp;c. But ſo far as you have gone, you have outgone them: they have ſpoken holily, and very uſefully; but what you utter is Bible all, &amp; your thoughts are apples of ſilver, are placed in pictures of gold. Your laſt
<pb facs="tcp:110756:6"/>Book, (<hi>i. e.</hi> a ſheet of Chriſts ſatisfaction I ſent him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted me with that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, better than I was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but this hath gone dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per into my heart, I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this with me, when I went to God, and like <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>'s Roll, I ſpread ſome of theſe Papers before me; and if like him, I did not weep ſore, I have the more reaſon to grieve, that I did not ſo grieve. Had I been young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and my eyes better, I would have Tranſcribed, if not all, yet ſome of theſe ſo pious Meditations. But if my Head be not laid, before they come out in Print, I ſhall with
<pb facs="tcp:110756:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the firſt get one of the Books. The good God bleſs your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavours with ſuitable ſucceſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> My honoured good Mother, this (with like encouragements,) hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened me to preſent you thus publickly, what I thought to have done in my own Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing It is true, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Mr. <hi>Rob: Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi>'s occaſional reflections, were put into my hand, more than a year agon, by a Lady happy in a near re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to that truly honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, both Gentleman, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; and I had thoughts of preſenting you the fruits of my plowing with his heifer, but they being catcht from me by
<pb facs="tcp:110756:7"/>a Friend, who liked them too well or too ill to reſtore them, I had not till now, any Eſſay of a Subject and language pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſend you. The illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentleman I laſt named, hath very praiſe-worthily ſet upon the reducing of both Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and Divinity, from aery, opinionative, and talka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to ſolid, experimental, and demonſtrative. As for Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, (though I rejoyce in his, and the Royal Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties labours for it, (if I had brains, I have nor time nor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the extreme ſtudies thereof: but as for Divinity, I ſhould have a thouſand joyes, if this, or any endeavour of
<pb facs="tcp:110756:8"/>mine, ſhould make for its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming from controverſial to practical, in any one ſoul; for ſure I am, the exercize of my heart, in pouring out ſuch So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liloquies to the Lord in my Cloſet, ſtand me in much more ſtead, than a thouſand Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes about that Mint and Cummin, which ſlayes the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral regard of the weighty things of the Law, in <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> But to ſo mean a Preſent, why preface I ſo many words? I will end with onely congratulating my ſelf this, That whereas the glory of ſome Children is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their Fathers, mine, is my Mother too; for as I glory in
<pb facs="tcp:110756:8"/>having a Father, who is able better to ſerve the Faith and Joy of Chriſtians; ſo I do in having a Mother, who ere now has, and I am ſure will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain encourage by her kindeſt acceptance, the weak endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of. My gracious Deareſt Mother,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very affectionate Son, and obedient Servant,</hi> Philo-Jeſus, Philo-Carolus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:9"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE TO THE READER</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong before the World was perplext with unprofitable Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in Philoſophy, and deſtructive Controverſies in Divinity, <hi>Solomon</hi> complain'd of multiplicity of Books; But ſurely, not of ſuch as were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to mend the World, and were likely to anſwer the end of the Authors, for he wrote much himſelf of Beaſts, Foules, creeping things, and Fiſhes, and of Trees, from the Cedar in <hi>Lebanon</hi> to the <hi>Hyſſop</hi> that ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of the Wall; moreover beſide theſe books of natural
<pb facs="tcp:110756:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Philoſophy, his books which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Canon are a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of the <hi>Hagiographa;</hi> If that which is written be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, even words of truth, and delightfully compoſed, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived for efficacy, like the words of the wiſe, which are as Goads and nails faſtned by the Nailers of Aſſemblies, no man of <hi>Solomons</hi> mind will complain. Books are faulty, it muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged; many of them ſo faulty, either as unſound, or prophane, or ridiculouſly ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that they are more fit for Fuell, then the Library of any man: But were all ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to the flame executed; it cannot be expected that any one of the ſurviving books in all its parts ſhould find Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick accptance, nor indeed that any one, except the myſteries of the Holy Ghoſt, ſhould pleaſe all men of unqueſtionable fidelity,
<pb facs="tcp:110756:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and skill to peruſe it; yet, Reader, Allow it to be ſaid of this book, (uot as peculiar to it) If it be impartially read, and rightly underſtood, according to the intendment of the Author, it will commend it ſelf. The words and phraſe where figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Tragical, require not a profound judgment to diſcern the meaning, unto ſuch as are well acquainted with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and able to judge of his excellent endowments, it is a ſufficient commendation of this book, that though it bear not his name he will own it; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will come to the hands of divers ſtrangers, eſpecially in this City, to them much may be ſaid concerning it, and him. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> ſayes of the vertuous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Many have done well, but thou excelleſt them all.</hi> Reader, if thou art apt to take offence, perhaps thou wilt now take off
<pb facs="tcp:110756:10"/>thine eye, and cloſe the Book, leſt it follow in the next line. After the ſame manner may be ſpoken of the Authour of this Book. But diſcreet perſons being better pleaſed with a juſt Title to a good character, than to find it upon record; The Friends of the Authour, although they know his mind is inriched far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ordinary rate of men of his years, and that he made good improvement of his time, while he was exercized in this work, which he offers to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, will forbear giving him this Encomium; yet without offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any violence to his modeſty, or the credit of former Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of their soliloquies, it may be ſaid, that among all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of this kind, imparted to the world, a more pure Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtile is not to be found. That ſpirit of Atheiſm and blaſphemy,
<pb facs="tcp:110756:11"/>that haunts the Wits of our times, diſplays it ſelf moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently, in quibling and drol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon the Bible, making a mock of all that is ſober and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred; depreciating, debaſing, and (what in them lyes,) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauching the very lip and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Holy Spirit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>This Authors innocent abuſe of Scripture, is ſo far from coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing, that it rather ſhames and condemns that licencious and abominable practiſe: Nor can we admit of the moſt uſeful al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, without that harmleſs, (nay helpful and advantagious) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or abuſe here practiced; Wherein the words, are indeed uſed to another, but yet to an Holy end &amp; purpoſe, beſides that for which they were at firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and intended; The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, (not playing with that
<pb facs="tcp:110756:11"/>
               <hi>Edge-tool,</hi> but) indeavouring only, to cut with both ſides of that <hi>two edged-ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Beautiful Captive, was to have her head ſhaved, and her nails, (not pared, but) made to grow, and the ſhaving her head, was the readieſt way, to make her nails to grow, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.12. All means were to be uſed, to make her ugly and deformed, (It is a ſhame for a Woman, to be ſhorn or ſhaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.6.) So to take off an <hi>Iſraelites</hi> affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from her; Let it be ſo ſtill, with all humane Wit and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Divine truth alone, may be fair and lovely, but when the former of theſe, is no Enemy, no Competitrix, no Rival, but an Handmaid to the latter, then let both grow together, until the Harveſt, yea let both Run toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and be Glorified. It is hoped, that the Candid Reader,
<pb facs="tcp:110756:12"/>will underſtand things up other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then is intended by the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Author; as when he ſaith of Meditation, that it hath told him, all that ever he did, yea and all that ever his God did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, undoubtedly his meaning is, that ſo far as he knoweth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right either his own or his Gods doings, he is beholding for it, to ſelf reflection, and Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: what he has written with a Sober, and unprejudiced mind, and of all the profit which thou ſhalt receive, give the glory to God, and thou wilt pleaſe the author, and alſo</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine to ſerve in any Office of love,</hi> Thomas Harriſon. Daniel Rolls.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:12"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEfore thou turneſt to the following pages, I could wiſh for thy regards to theſe few particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Though my youth, and ſins, and ſufferings therein, make my acquaintance with Books much narrower than I could deſire, yet on that acquaintance I have, I dare humbly to give it thee as my opinion, that our modern writers have very much departed from this way of Inſinuating Piety, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious meditations and ſoliloquies, in which, the fathers and ancient <hi>Hero</hi>'s of divinity were very happy, and have been for ſome centuries very ſerviceable.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> I ſhould (for reaſons ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeven) think that this Age were
<pb facs="tcp:110756:13"/>to be dealt with, in it; much more congruouſly, than in thoſe other more inſiſted on; of the regular of which, I cannot think of one, which might not receive full great advantages from this; from this I ſay, which with the catechetical one, I pray God revive among us. Let ancient records come out of their duſt, and they ſhall bear me witneſs, that there was never age from Chriſt to our own, which ſtood in more need of reductives from an Aery profeſſional, I know not what, called religion, unto devotional and Practical Piety, the power of Godlineſſe! At this the following eſſay drives, the good Lord ſucceed it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Sith the joynt Juſtice and clemency of Magiſtrates, the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and writing of Miniſter s, the unparallell'd Judgements of the great God on us, (theſe late Years,) have bin all too little to keep Cities,
<pb facs="tcp:110756:13"/>Towns, Villages, or very families, from bandying into factions, and mens baiting each other with the epithets of Praelatiſt, Epiſcopalian, Preſbyterian, Independent, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, Arminian, Antinomian, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galiſt, and who can tell how many like; I have thought it as vain to intereſt my ſelf in the contentions of any, ſo very proper to commend the Practicks of Piety to all, in ſuch a way as this, which ſome judicious believe will offend none. I cannot think, but that there is of Iſrael, in each of thoſe Parties: and my hearts deſire and prayer to God for them is, that they may be ſaved. As far as I know my heart, I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer theſe ſheets to go abroad to ſerve the faith and joy of each of them: let them all forgive me this wrong, I confeſs my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The worſt Servant of <hi>Chriſt, P P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:110756:14"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle to the Reader; <hi>Pag.</hi> 15 For Nailers, read Maſters of Aſſemblies. <hi>P.</hi> 16. for Tragical read Tropical, for Samuel read Lemuel in the Epiſtle to the Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110756:14"/>
            <head>1. <hi>A</hi> Soliloquy <hi>with</hi> Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy <hi>it ſelf.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H Meditation! I ſee thee, and now I will leave my<note n="(a)" place="margin">Joh. 4.28, 29.</note> water-pots, and go call all mankind to come and ſee the Duty that told me all that ever I did; ay, and that my God ever did.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Lu. 11.27.</note> Bleſſed is the womb of that Grace, that bears thee, and the paps that gave thee ſuck.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 5.6.</note> Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs, for they ſhall be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with thee!<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 2.18.</note> The fair <hi>Rachel</hi> of piety, may cry out her eyes, for children, and holy ſeed, and break her heart, becauſe they are not, if ſhe be not impregnated by theel<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſa. 113.9.</note> Thou makeſt barren Graces to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110756:15"/>keep houſe, and to be the joyful mothers of children. Thou ſuffereſt no<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 105.44.</note> man, nor devil to do them harm, thou rebukeſt the Prince of darkneſs for their ſakes. They that will be<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Ti. 6.9.</note> rich in thee, will not fall into many temptations! for by thee, one Grace will chaſe a<note n="(h)" place="margin">Deu. 32.30.</note> thouſand, and two put ten thouſand to flight! Thy<note n="(i)" place="margin">Job 13.11.</note> Excellency makes them afraid, and thy dread falls upon them! Thou<note n="(k)" place="margin">Plal. 104.32.</note> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt on earthy affections, and they tremble! thou toucheſt the hills of corruption, and they ſmoke! In thy Name I have caſt out devils! and over thee the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> gates of hell can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevail! Thou art, as it were, an Emmanuel, God with us! In thee grace and peace do live, move, and have their being! Thou rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt down manna, and giveſt Angels food to them whoſe ſoul<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſa. 107.18.</note> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth all manner of meat, and draws near to the gates of death! If thy<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſa. 11.3.</note> foundations be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what can the righteous do?
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110756:15"/>Thou delivereſt in<note n="(o)" place="margin">Job 5.19, 26.</note> ſix, yea ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven troubles! in ſpiritual famine from death, and war from the ſword! Thou haſt made a<note n="(p)" place="margin">Job 1.10.</note> hedge about piety, about her houſe, and all that ſhe has, on every ſide! thou bleſſeſt the work of her hands!<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pro. 29.18.</note> Where there is none of thy viſion, the people periſh; but in thy light we ſee light! Thou<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 7.5.</note> caſteſt out the motes out of thy own eye, and ſeeſt clearly to caſt out the beams of ours! Thou<note n="(s)" place="margin">Luk. 1.76, 79.</note> ſhalt be called the prophet of the Higheſt; for thou goeſt before the face of the Lord, to prepare his way! thou giveſt light to them who ſit in darkneſs and in the ſhadow of death!<note n="(t)" place="margin">Job 28.13.</note> Man knoweth not thy price, neither is it found in the I and of the living. The<note n="(u)" place="margin">Job 29.13, 15, 16.</note> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of him that was ready to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, has come on thee a thouſand times 1 for thou art eyes to the blind, and legs to the lame! a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the poor; and that which thou knoweſt not, thou ſearcheſt out
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110756:16"/>Thou<note n="(x)" place="margin">Job 35.11.</note> teacheſt us more than the beaſts of the earth, &amp; makeſt us wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than the fowls of heaven! I<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.93.</note> will never forget thy precepts, for with them thou haſt quickned me! and ſure I am of thoſe who follow thee.<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſa. 73.5.</note> They are not in trouble as other men, neither are they plagued as other men. To what<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.11.</note> purpoſe is the multitude of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices without thee? without thee the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Am. 5.18.</note> day of the Lord is darkneſs, and not light! I have ſaid, That without thee it<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mal. 3.14.</note> is vain to ſerve God, and what profit is it that we have kept his ordinance? Faith comes not by<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ro. 10.17.</note> hearing, without thee; yea, without thee, the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 21.13.</note> Houſe of prayer is a den of thieves! thieves that break through and ſteal, duty and comfort! Hope, without thee<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ro. 5.5.</note> maketh aſham'd; and Repentance, without thee, is to<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Co 7.10.</note> be repented of! Without thee, ſin doth<note n="(h)" place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> eaſily beſet us! and methinks thou art the in-door<note n="(i)" place="margin">Zec. 13.1.</note> fountain, opened for ſin, and for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110756:16"/>uncleaneſs! without thee, the whole<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.5.</note> Head of piety is ſick, and the whole heart is faint! Thou art the Apothecary to the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Mar. 9.12.</note> phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician of ſouls! There is no<note n="(m)" place="margin">Jer. 8.22.</note> Balm in the <hi>Gilead</hi> of the Goſpel; and there's no phyſician there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee! Duties without thee, are phyſicians<note n="(n)" place="margin">Job 13.4.</note> of no value! tis thou<note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Co 7.1.</note> perfecteſt holineſs in the fear of God! 'Tis impoſſible to ſerve thee<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> and mammon! Thy two<note n="(q)" place="margin">Mar. 12.42.</note> mites, make ſuch a farthing, which I had rather preſent the Lord with, than with<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mie. 6.7.</note> thouſands of rams, and ten thouſands of rivers of oyl!<note n="(s)" place="margin">Luk. 7.22, 23.</note> Bleſſed is he, whoſoever is not offended in thee, who makeſt the blind to ſee, the lame to walk, the leper to be cleanſed, the deaf to hear, the very dead to be raiſed!<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 22.1.</note> Oh my Soliloquy! my Soliloquy! why haſt thou for ſaken me? why art thou ſo far from helping me?<note n="(u)" place="margin">Can. 1.6.</note> Tell me, oh Meditation, thou whom my ſoul loveth, why ſhould <hi>I</hi> be, as one that turneth aſide by the flocks
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110756:17"/>of thy companions?<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſa. 42.2.</note> As the Hart pants after the water-brooks; ſo panteth my ſoul after thee! My ſoul thirſteth for thee, in this deſart land,<note n="(y)" place="margin">De. 32.10.</note> and howling wilderneſs, to lead me about, and inſtruct me!<note n="(z)" place="margin">Ex. 28.36.</note> 'Tis thou onely that canſt grave like the ingraving of a ſignet, on the plate of my heart, holineſs to the Lord!<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ge. 3.13.</note> For really, without thee, the ſerpents will beguile me, and <hi>I</hi> ſhall eat!<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ge. 4.13.</note> and my ſin will be greater than <hi>I</hi> can bear, as <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid. At every fools bidding, my own and all,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Job 2.9.</note> I ſhall curſe God, and dye, if thou ſtand not by me! What are my gifts, graces, duties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without thee?<note n="(d)" place="margin">Job 4.21.</note> Doth not their excellency which is in them, go away, and they dye without wiſdom?<note n="(e)" place="margin">Job 5.14.</note> Don't they meet in darkneſs in the day-time? and grope in noon-day, as in the night? 'Twas ever well, when thou and I<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſa. 55.14.</note> took ſweet councel together, and walk'd unto the Houſe of the Lord in company.<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.24.</note> Ah! I will eaſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110756:17"/>me of my Adverſaries, and be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of thoſe enemies, which keep thee and me apart!<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.22.</note> Let not thy ſilver be mixt with droſs, nor thy wine with water, and thou ſhalt be preferred to my chiefeſt joy!<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal. 137.1, 6.</note> While I ſit down by the rivers of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and weep in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Zion, Thou, oh Soliloquy!<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſa. 139.3.</note> thou ſhalt compaſs my path, and my lying down: Thou ſhalt be acquainted with all my wayes,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Can. 1.13.</note> Thou ſhalt be to me as a bundle of myrrhe, and lye betwixt my breaſts all the night long!<note n="(m)" place="margin">Can. 4.16.</note> Thou ſhalt blow upon my garden, and make the ſpices to flow forth, that <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah Jeſus</hi> may come in, and eat his pleaſant fruit.<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſa. 119.127.</note> So will I love thy commands above gold, yea, above fine gold!<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ge. 2.24.</note> I will leave father, and mother, and wife too, and cleave to thee. <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:110756:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>2.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God, of Created things.</head>
            <p>OH my God!<note n="(p)" place="margin">Heb. 4.13.</note> There is no creature which is not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in thy ſight! But alas! that there is any ſuch thing as a creature, or that there ever was ſuch a work as Creation, is hardly manifeſt to mine.<note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Co 5.17.</note> It coſt thee a ſecond crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of me, to make me believe the firſt! For that the world was made by Chriſt, I never believ'd, 'tis I was made by him too: And it may well be faid,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Eph. 3.9.</note> Thou haſt created all things by Chriſt Jeſus, ſince the very Faith, of all things being cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, is by him alſo; it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that man ſhould rightly know himſelf<note n="(s)" place="margin">Gal. 6.15.</note> to be any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 'till he is a new one! They are not many thouſands of years paſt, ſince there was no being, but thy own; nor indeed is there any now,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110756:18"/>whoſe name is, <hi>Jam,</hi> or is not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Nothing, than a Being, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thy own! but as if when thou created'ſt ours, thou hadſt annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thy own, and thou hadſt ceaſed to be, ſcon after we began to be; how art thou as ſar out of mind, as out of ſight, with me, for the moſt part? How rarely, and faintly, do I ſay,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Job 19.25.</note> I know that my Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or my Creator either liveth! So difficult it is to weak Faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thee the Maker of heaven and earth, that I am put hard to it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, to think thee the Maker of that little ſpot and clod of earth that I carry about me. I am ſo bad at remembring thee, the worlds Creator, that I have much ado to remember thee, my very own. But did<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 12.1.</note> I not live, move, and have<note n="(x)" place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note> my Being in thee, the fault would be leſs heinous, and monſtrous. Thou art nigher to me, than I am to my ſelf; and I have as perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and neceſſarily, thy upholding, as my own ſubſiſting: ſo that did I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110756:19"/>not forget my ſelf, I could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly forget thee: Nay, and did I not forget all things, 'twere impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible but I muſt remember their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, being all bear thy ſuperſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yea, and aloud ſay of thee, It is he that hath made us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37 17.</note> and not we our ſelves.<note n="(z)" place="margin">1 Ti. 4.4.</note> Every creature of God, is good to teach me, were I but good to learn; its being a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and God being its Creator! But, oh my God! I neither learn of creatures, to honour their Creator; nor of the Creator, to ſcorn crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures! I can very ſeldome ſee, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thee as thou art in thy ſelf; or them as they are in themſelves. I converſe much with both, and yet but little, becauſe I converſe with thee without thy Attributes, and with them without theirs; not view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as inſufficient, or thee as alſufficient.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 54.5.</note> If thou my Maker, (as the prophet ſpeaks) art my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and jealouſie be the rage of a man himſelf; ſure it concerns me, to look better to my wayes, than to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110756:19"/>go a whoring after the idols of my fooliſh imagination. I find to my wo, I converſe moſtly with nothings, not with thee the Creator, or thy creatures; but with the idols and creatures of my own corrupt fancy. For as there is no ſuch God. as I but too oft conceive thee: ſo there are no ſuch-creatures, as I oft con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them to be. There is no God leſs than omnipotent; there are no creatures more than nullipotent. I am making an idol, not worſhipping thee, when I contemplate of thee otherwiſe, than of an Albeing God! and I am ſetting my<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pro. 23.5.</note> eyes on that which is not, when I am meditating of them, as any other, than as very Nothings, as to ſubſiſtence, without thy providence, as they were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence, without thy creation. There were variableneſs with thee indeed, and more than ſhadow of turning, if thou wert not as Albeing a God now, as before thou madeſt all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: and ſure if I, and all thy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, were more than No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110756:20"/>and if thou wert not-the very Being of our beings, thou couldſt not ſo be. Teach me then, oh my God! teach me to have all creatures manifeſt in my ſight, and thee the Creator alſo! Shew me manifeſtly, That thou Art as really, and to Faith as apparently, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being God and Good, as thou waſt before the world began; and that all thy creatures Beings, conſiſt in being Nothing without thee now, as before they ever were manifeſt to me. Oh my God! how thou haſt made Nothings, but very Nothings! not one Being, that has any Beings more, without that which it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives from thy prouidence, than it had without that, which it drew from thy creation. Not being, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, is as eſſential to a creature, as being by thee. For could it be any thing without thee, its name would be <hi>I am,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſa. 40.6.</note> and it muſt be a God. And wo is me, if I deny the Unity of the Godhead, as oft as I think of created Beings, without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110756:20"/>the thought of their not Being, it being not poſſible that thou ſhouldſt be, <hi>I Am:</hi> if there be any beſide thee, or if there be any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide thee, which is not a Nothing without thee! Every creature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares by its experience, that God is its<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Co. 15.28.</note> All in All; and God works all its works, in it, and for it. Lord make my ſoul (the worſt of thy creatures) to make thee its All in All; the Being of its being, and of all other beings, neither conceiving of thee as leſs than All things, or of the world, more than a Nothing. I may loſe it, and loſe nothing; but were it ſo, that I could ſave my ſoul, and loſe thee, I ſhould loſe my All. I may gain a world, and gain juſt nothing; but could I gain thee with the very loſs of my ſoul, I ſhould gain all things! For, ſure I am, gain is of Good onely, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 19.7.</note> There is none Good but God; thy Self, oh my God, who doſt truly ſay to thy creatures all, without me ye can do nothing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:110756:21"/>
            <head>
               <hi>3.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with the Soul, of the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</head>
            <p>I Will now go to my ſoul, I will conſider her wayes, and be wiſe. Come now, and let us reaſon toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, oh my ſoul! If I ſhould aſk that, which was once God's Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, From whence conneſt thou? I doubt you muſt return, that which was once the devil's Anſwer;<note n="(f)" place="margin">Job 2.2.</note> From going to and fro in the earth. The earth, which he hath<note n="(g)" place="margin">Job 38.6.</note> hang'd on nothing, and charg'd you to lay no ſtreſs upon, while you keep in this my<note n="(h)" place="margin">Co. 4.7.</note> earthen Veſſel, your life, indeed, muſt be on earth; but<note n="(i)" place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> your converſation in heaven. I would that you ſo uſe the world, as not abuſing it, or your ſelf! You are both poor enough, and you know who bids you, wrong not the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110756:21"/>poor, becauſe the Lord is their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. If you tell me, That God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd all that he made<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ge. 1.31.</note> very good: I muſt tell you, So it was, and ſo it is, for Gods ends with it. But whether it be not as very ill for your ends with it, is a doubt; He intended all for his own glory: for which 'tis good and fit, if you intend it for yours, you will find it much otherwiſe; becauſe though<note n="(l)" place="margin">i Co. 1.27.</note> God has choſe, even the fooliſh things of the world, to manifeſt his wiſedom with: you muſt chuſe the wiſe ones of a better world; to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt yours. God that ſo loved the world, as you know, bids you not to love it, as you are not ignorant of; for the earth he has given into the hands of the ſons of men, but 'tis himſelf he gives to the Son of God: And becauſe he reſolv'd to ſatisfie them, that they ſhould, and could have no more, he calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf their<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſ 16.5. La. 3.24.</note> portion and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with content in it ſelf, their great gain; pearl of price, and one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110756:22"/>thing neceſſary. Oh my ſoul! The mighty Lord who humbles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to behold the things that are done in earth, calls thee to look up to him in heaven, making the earth thy footſtool, as well as his own. Knowing the emptineſs of the earth, and of the fulneſs thereof; knowing the creature not onely ſubject to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but altogether lighter; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all made things to be but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, he charges thee to truſt in none of their vanities. I hope for ſalvation from none of their hills, but to ſay of all creatures, as he of all men;<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſa. 14.3.</note> There is none that doth good, no not one. Ponder it then, oh my ſoul! though thy ſelf art a very nothing; and if it be worth my while to loſe thee, to gain the world, yet ſure, it were a hard bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to loſe thy God for ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds: yea obſerve, whoever parts with God, parts with him for nothing, though it be to ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all he has. And do but think how heinouſly God muſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110756:22"/>needs take it, That of Nothings themſelves, any thing ſhould be thought too much to part with, for him who is our All. What thinkeſt thou, oh my ſoul! of Popiſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Merit? we our ſelves are but Nothings, without God; our ſervices are leſs, and are incapable of being greater than our ſelves. Our God is our All, if we give him any thing that's good, we muſt give him his own goodneſs; and 'tis a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious way of meriting, to give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one his own. Take heed to your ſelf of this leaven, and know, You have, and are nothing, but what is Gods own. I adjure thee by the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, That thou for ever ſeek him, as no leſs than thy All; that thou tell him, That though every thing he made anſwers his Ends, 'tis He onely, that made every thing, can anſwer thine. That thou ſay plainly, That unleſs he be all things, he is a poor God: All he has beſide himſelf, being very Nothing to thy wants and deſires, and ſuch as leaves
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110756:23"/>thee in ſtraits, in the very<note n="(o)" place="margin">Job 20.22.</note> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its ſufficiency. Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, oh my ſoul! that wherever in a Duty, Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he gives in of himſelf, to a poor Nothing ſpirit, 'tis<note n="(p)" place="margin">Job 3.17.</note> there the wicked ceaſe from troubling, and there the weary are at reſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="soliloquy">
            <head>
               <hi>4.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God, about Piety.</head>
            <p>OH my God! even<note n="(q)" place="margin">Job 4.8.</note> as I have ſeen, They that plow iniquity, and ſow wickedneſs, reap the ſame:<note n="(r)" place="margin">&amp; 20.</note> They are deſtroyed from morning to evening, they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for ever, none regarding it, Were it of neceſſary choice, I vow I had rather have the very devil my Gueſt, than<note n="(s)" place="margin">Ro. 7.17.</note> the ſin that dwelleth in me; and have Satan my Tyrant, than ſin my King. Other evils are drones, it is ſin<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Co. 15.56.</note> which is the ſting
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110756:23"/>of all. Make me any thing what thou pleaſeſt, beſides<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iſa. 45.99</note> a ſtriver with my Maker, the<note n="(x)" place="margin">Deu 32.33.</note> wine of which contention, is the poyſon of dragons, and venom of aſps. Oh my God! I read that<note n="(y)" place="margin">2 Ti 4.3.</note> godlineſs is profitable unto all things; if ſo, it muſt be profitable to ſin it ſelf; I mean, the finding, driving, and keeping it out, and profitable to it ſelf, in maintaining, feeding, and cloathing it ſelf well.<note n="(z)" place="margin">2. iT 6.6.</note> With con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent herein. I am told 'tis great gain, and I proteſt I believe it, becauſe as thou doſt<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſa. 4.3.</note> ſet a part him that is godly, for thy ſelf: ſo he that is godly, ſets apart thee for himſelf. Methinks it is a ſtrange queſtion,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ex. 15.11.</note> who is like unto thee— Glorious in holineſs? Lord, I would aſk thee, Who has any glory or holineſs, but is juſt like thee? and that with a likeneſs of participation and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation. Were I aſk'd, to whom I would liken God, I would anſwer (in both thoſe wayes) to every Saint on earth. For,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Joh. 5.22.</note> as the Father
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110756:24"/>judgeth no man; ſo neither do they, but commit all judgment to God the Son: As<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ge. 18.25.</note> the Judge of the whole earth doth right,<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Pe. 1.17.</note> ſo doe they, and that<note n="(f)" place="margin">Phil. 2.15.</note> without reſpect of perſons, their own, or others! The ſame mind is in them, that was in God our Saviour; and I may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay of Saints wills-deliberate<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ro. 9.19.</note> who hath reſiſted his will? To will, juſt as God wills, is<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ro. 7.18.</note> preſent with them: Thou chuſeſt them, and they chuſe thee; and they are a chuſing, as well as<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Pe 2.9. Luke 10.42.</note> a choſen, Generation: Among their affections, there is not one (habitual) Non conformiſt. The very love of God<note n="(k)" place="margin">1 Jo. 4.16.</note> dwells in them; their love and Gods has one object: and 'tis no other than that God hates, which they hate! if God loves his enemy, they<note n="(l)" place="margin">Mat. 5.14.</note> do ſo to: if he hates themſelves, they will do ſo too: Their way is to follow and imitate God, and nothing ſatisfies them, but his<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſ. 17.15.</note> likeneſs: They never think they have done like themſelves, ſave when they have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110756:24"/>done like Chriſt Jeſus. They make the very graven image, and likeneſs of him that is above, in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation here below on the earth. Their very eating, drinking, and ſleeping bears the image and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Chriſt on it; and if any word or deed be not conformed to his likeneſs, ſeaſon'd with juſtice, like ſalt, they diſown and renounce it, and would not have it imputed by God unto them, for the whole earth. I may then call Saints,<note n="(n)" place="margin">i Co 11.7.</note> the image and glory of God, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs image and likeneſs of him! O my God, my God! Let this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thine be mine; and let not my heart or life be disfigured by my corruptions and temptations, which<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mat. 6.7.</note> uſe vain repetitions, as the heathen do, thinking that they ſhall be heard for their much ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, againſt thy likeneſs. Scatter my proud<note n="(p)" place="margin">Lu. 1.51, 52.</note> luſts, pull down the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ones from their ſeats, exalt my likeneſs to thee, which is of ſo low degree: Hear me, oh my God!
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110756:25"/>what I ſay, e're I give ſleep to my eyes, or ſlumber to my eye-lids.<note n="(q)" place="margin">Job 6.8, 9.</note> Oh that might have my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and that God would grant me the thing I long for! Even that it would pleaſe God to deſtroy my unlikene ſs to himſelf; and that he would let looſe his hand, and cut it off!</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="soliloquy">
            <head>
               <hi>5.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf.</head>
            <p>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Pro. 10.26.</note> AS vineger to the teeth, and as ſmoke to the eyes: ſo is a ſluggiſh heart, to them that ſend it towards thee. Oh piety!<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pro. 13.7.</note> There is, that maketh himſelf rich without thee, yet hath nothing! There is, that maketh himſelf poor with thee, yet hath great riches.<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 9.10.</note> They that know thy Name, will put their truſt in thee; for thou haſt not forſaken them, that ſeek thee!
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110756:25"/>They that ſeek thee early, will find thee; and they that find thee, never loſe their way. If God himſelf make me happy without thee, he muſt make me happy without happineſs.<note n="(u)" place="margin">Mat 8.8.</note> I am not worthy indeed, that thou ſhouldſt come under my roof! becauſe in my houſe, there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manſions of thy implacable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, becauſe too too often I have<note n="(x)" place="margin">Mat 7.6.</note> given thy ſacred things to dogs, and thy pearl to ſwine. I have killed the counſels and rebukes that were thy prophets, and ſtoned the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors that were ſent unto me! I have ſometimes betrayed thee with a kiſs, and calling thee Lord, done thee diſſervice! Sometimes, I have hid thy Talent in a Napkin, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhile ſacrific'd to thee, with the ſtrange fire of blind zeal, fire prepared by the devil and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels! I have ſeen thee a ſtranger, and not took thee in! Naked, and cloathed thee not, ſo much as with the garment of praiſe! Sick and in priſon haſt thou been, and I not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110756:26"/>thee! Nay, I have cry'd with the rabble,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Lu. 23.21.</note> Crucifie him, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him! I will<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſal. 38.18.</note> declare my ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and I will be ſorry for my ſin. I will now count all things but dung that I may win thee! Though thou ſlayeſt me, I will put my truſt in thee, and the loftineſs of my looks to thee, ſhall never be humbled! Open, oh piety! open thou my lips, and my mouth ſhall ſpeak forth thy praiſe! in thee I'le<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note> live, move, and have my being! I'le luſt after no other beauty, thy<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pro. 5.19.</note> breaſts ſhall ſatisfie me at all times, and I'le be raviſht alwayes with thy love! I'le fight the devil, and wreſtle with God for thee!</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110756:26"/>
            <head>
               <hi>6.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God about his Law.</head>
            <p>OH my God, my God!<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſa. 2.1. Job 21.1.</note> Why do the Heathen rage! and the people of the earth ſet themſelves againſt the Lord, and his Chriſt: Why ſay they to thee, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes? Why cant they abide Chriſt's Goſpel<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mal. 3.2.</note> coming, and endure that he ſhould appear? Does<note n="(e)" place="margin">Heb. 7.19.</note> thy Law make nothing perfect? yes it does. It makes the world<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſa 139.2.</note> hate thee, with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hatred, and count thee its ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my! Thy Law which binds the Kings of their luſts, in chains, and their Nobles in fetters of iron;<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſa. 135 8.</note> which ſmites the firſt born of their <hi>Egypt,</hi> and daſheth their little ones againſt the ſtones, makes them ſay to the whole Trinity,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mat 25.</note> Depart
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110756:27"/>ye curſed, and call to the devil,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Jud. 9.11.</note> as all the trees to the Bramble, Come thou and reign over us! Oh my God,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ro. 7.7.</note> I had not known my own ſin, or other mens, but by the Law; for the ſake of which<note n="(l)" place="margin">Gal. 3.29.</note> Schoolmaſter, the whole world is out of love with thy School,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mat 5.19.</note> Had Chriſt made an end of the Law. I ſee none would have been offended in him; but I ſee now, his firſt Sermon has made him thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of rebells. But till the Fifth chapter of <hi>Matthew</hi> be blotted out, there's no hope of their return: They will ſtill pray, That<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat 6.9, 10, 13.</note> their Father which is in hell, his name may be hallow'd; That his kingdom? may come, and his will be done, in earth as 'tis in hell; That his may be the kingdom, the power, and the glory, for ever and ever. But oh my God! were<note n="(o)" place="margin">Job 6.25.</note> right words forcible, and would arguing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, there were ſome hope! For, alas! alas haſt thou not made it<note n="(p)" place="margin">Jam 1.29.</note> perfect liberty, as perfect law?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110756:27"/>And have not the<note n="(q)" place="margin">Ro. 8 21.</note> ſons of God a glorious liberty, whom God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains from nothing, but<note n="(r)" place="margin">Joh. 8.32.</note> ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery; and exacts nothing from, but to<note n="(s)" place="margin">Mat. 5.4.</note> be like himſelf! Lord, Thou haſt commanded nothing that I know of, but the<note n="(t)" place="margin">Ex. 20.</note> having no other God beſide thee, and what hurt is in this, there is no other to have! And if we make an idol, that is, a Nothing, what true plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is theré in ſerving ſuch a Lye, any more than in making it? If it be<note n="(u)" place="margin">Mal. 3.14.</note> vain to ſerve any God, ſure 'tis ſo, to ſerve a vain one, as a<note n="(x)" place="margin">Phi. 3.19.</note> Belly, and the other gods of this world! Oh my God! in taking humane nature on me, I have took on me<note n="(y)" place="margin">Phi. 2.7.</note> the form of a ſervant; and his ſervant I am, to whom<note n="(z)" place="margin">Ro. 6.16.</note> I obey: could I find a better Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, I would not ſay as <hi>David,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſa. 116.10.</note> I am thy ſervant, I am thy ſervant! I would ſay of this thy Law, 'Tis a hard ſaying, who can bear it? Nay, I would<note n="(b)" place="margin">pſal. 2.3.</note> break this Bond in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and caſt this cord behind my
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110756:28"/>back, if I could! But ſeeing<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſa. 44.6</note> thou art God, and there is none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee. If this Law be a<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat 11.30.</note> yoke, I'le ſay it, 'tis an eaſie one; and if any burden, light enough in conſcience, a burden that I would not be without for my head, and a yoke, I had rather loſe my neck, than loſe it. If there be any<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Co 4.17.</note> weight in it, 't is a weight of glory; and if at any time it ſeem<note n="(f)" place="margin">Heb 12.11.</note> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, I am ſure it does ſeem ſo one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but afterwards bringeth forth the peaceable fruit, which unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives us. I am ſure, as many as have known the good of it, have took joyfully the<note n="(g)" place="margin">Heb 10.34.</note> ſpoiling of all other goods for it. If it mar any mirth, how comes<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> fulneſs of joy into thy preſence? If it check pleaſures, how flouriſh they ſo at thy right hand? Sure enough, this Law is in full force there: if it confine a man, <hi>David</hi> took an ill courſe to walk<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal. 119 45.</note> at liberty, when he choſe to live by it, for that end: and they err, who call thy ſervice perfect freedom; if
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110756:28"/>it makes valour flat, how come<note n="(k)" place="margin">pro. 2 8.</note> the righteous to be bold as lions? and they that violate it, to flee, when none purſue! Oh my God! I do confeſs, I am<note n="(l)" place="margin">Jam. 1.18.</note> a double-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man, and therefore unſtable in my wayes: I ſee that within me, which taſtes thy Law as<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mat 27.34.</note> vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and gall; but I have alſo that in me, which ſayes to thy Law, Thy<note n="(n)" place="margin">Can 4.11.</note> lips, oh my ſpouſe! drop as the honey-comb; honey and milk are under thy tongue, and the ſmell of thy garments is like the ſmell of Lebanon. I have that, which ſayes to thy Law,<note n="(o)" place="margin">1 Sa. 17.43.</note> Am I a dog, that thou comeſt to me with ſtaves! And I have that which rejoyns; yes, 'tis a dog, for the love of Chriſt beat it out. I have that indeliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which upon the devils,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat 3.9.</note> all theſe things I will give thee; will give the Law a repulſe: and I have that deliberacy, which if it might have<note n="(q)" place="margin">Nu. 22.18.</note> a houſe full of gold and ſilver, will not go beyond the word of thy Law, to do more or leſs. I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110756:29"/>have that which reſents<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mic. 4.</note> the beſt of thy Laws, as a briar; and the moſt upright, as a thorn hedge. And I have that, which in the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Mal. 3.7.</note> day or night, when it makes up its jewels, maketh<note n="(t)" place="margin">Job 28.18.</note> no mention of coral, or pearls, Ophirs gold, or the precious Sardonyx, but calls thy Law its<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iſa. 58.15.</note> delight, the ornament of Grace,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pro. 3.22.</note> life to my ſoul, and grace to my neck: and this I can truly aver,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſa. 139.21, 23.</note> I hate the men, and things, that hate thy Law, I am griev'd with thoſe that riſe up againſt it! I hate them with perfect hatred, and I count them my enemies. When thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſal. 341.5.</note> ſmites me, it is a kindneſs; when it reproves me, 'tis an excellent oyl. It breaks not my head with thoughts, how to break its own; but my heart with cares, how to get a plaiſter from Chriſt! For though I can't<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pro. 18.14.</note> bear an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken ſpirit, neither can I bear a wounded one! Some imagine, that the voice of thy Law is nothing, but Curſed be every one! But me
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110756:29"/>thinks I hear all thy Laws, ſaying with one mouth,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ge. 1.26.</note> Come let us make man in our own image! and their deſign ſeems to me, to be<note n="(c)" place="margin">Tit. 2 14.</note> the redeeming us from all iniquity, purifying us as a peculiar people, zealous of good works. Oh my God! none ever periſh'd by the Law falling on them, but by their own<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat 4.44.</note> falling firſt, on the Law; 'tis we break it, and our ſelves in it. If none are its<note n="(e)" place="margin">Joh. 15.14.</note> friends, but ſuch as do whatſoever it commands, I muſt ſtand out! But if<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ro. 13.10.</note> love unto, be the fulfilling of the Law, fure I am one, ſuch a one as 'tis. Though<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luk 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtus</hi> like, it tax the whole world, and meet not with any that payes it, ſo ſlender tribute of obedience, as my rebellious heart: Yet this, oh my God,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſa. 38.18.</note> I declare, I will declare my iniquity, and I will be ſorry for my ſin! For I muſt needs ſay of thy Law, as<note n="(i)" place="margin">Joh. 19.4, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Pilate</hi> of thy Son, I ſee no ſault in him! I will pray, That all its<note n="(k)" place="margin">Heb. 10.13.</note> enemies within me, may be made
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110756:30"/>its foot-ſtool, and that it may<note n="(l)" place="margin">Jude 14.15.</note> come into me, with ten thouſand of its arguments, to execute judgment upon all, and convince all ungodly luſts of their hard ſpeeches againſt it! and that now he may<note n="(m)" place="margin">Re. 2.27.</note> rule them with a rod of iron! For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Ro. 3 19.</note> the way of peace they have not known, except by fighting againſt it. Oh my God! let thy Law take away<note n="(o)" place="margin">Joh. 15.2.</note> every branch that beareth fruit, let it purge it, that it may bring forth more fruit! It hath of<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat 4.24.</note> old heal'd ſick peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, taken with divers diſeaſes and torments; thoſe that were poſſeſs'd with devils, thoſe which were lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick, and had the palſie! And ſure its<note n="(q)" place="margin">Nu. 11.23.</note> hand is not ſhortned, that it cannot ſave! It has of old, led ſouls into the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Can. 2.4, 5.</note> Banquetting houſe of the Goſpel, ſtaying them with its flagons, and comforting them with its apples, when they have been ſick of love to God, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to their ſins! Other<note n="(s)" place="margin">Iſa 3.12.</note> Ica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders cauſe poor ſouls to err. But,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110756:30"/>oh my God, let this<note n="(t)" place="margin">Luk 1.79.</note> Guide lead my feet into the way of peace!</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="soliloquy">
            <head>
               <hi>7.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God about his Promiſes.</head>
            <p>LOrd, when I turn to thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, I am ready to aſk my ſoul;<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pro 23.5.</note> Wilt thou ſet thine eyes on that which is not? as if thy mouth ſpake vanity, and thy right hand, were a right hand of lies!<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſa. 104.8.</note> Promiſes from God, think I,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Joh. 3 9.</note> how can theſe things be?<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſa. 113.9.</note> He humbles himſelf indeed, to behold the things that are done in heaven! But he won't humble them ſo low, as to bring them to us on earth to, will he?<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 16.19.</note> Whomſoever thou bindeſt to thy ſervice on earth, to them art thou bound, for reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each one in heaven? Lord,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 53.1.</note> who can believe this report? and to whom is this Arm of the Lord
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110756:31"/>revealed?<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pro. 19 4.</note> Every one is a friend to him that giveth gifts;<note n="(d)" place="margin">Jam 1.17.</note> and if ſo good &amp; perfect gifts, come down from thee, oh my God! Why is not every power of my ſoul, thy friend?<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pro. 18.16.</note> A mans gift maketh room for him, won't God's do ſo too? 'Tis good advice,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mar. 13.5.</note> Take heed leaſt any man deceive you! But what, am I affraid God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me too?<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſa. 119.86.</note> I hy command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are faithful, and are not<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ro. 4.16.</note> thy promiſes ſure? Are they call'd exceeding great, becauſe they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed belief and credibility?<note n="(i)" place="margin">2 re. 1.4.</note> and precious, becauſe too good to be true? Are their Yea and<note n="(k)" place="margin">2 Co 1 20.</note> Amen changeable into Nay, nay? and muſt my faith,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Jam. 2. 19.</note> as the devils, believe and tremble, while it does ſo? Shall I, oh my God! ſhall I think it not<note n="(m)" place="margin">He. 6 18.17.16.</note> impoſſible for thee to lie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my own incredulouſneſs, has made thee ſwear? Do mens oaths put an end to ſtrife,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Luk 1.37.</note> and ſhall not thine? Muſt I be jealous, that thy Word is the more infirm, becauſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110756:31"/>firm'd by an oath? Oh fooliſh brute,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> who hath bewitched me? Oh my God, my God!<note n="(p)" place="margin">Acts 2.39.</note> thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to me and my children, are to them that are afar off from belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them! We make<note n="(q)" place="margin">Mat 22.5.</note> light of them, and go every one our wayes; one to his Book, another to his play: A fit of ſickneſs, a ſtorm at Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will make me cry.<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat 14 18.</note> Bring them hither to me; but alas even then,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Mat 22.14.</note> though many are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, few are choſen; they cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me ſatisfactorily,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Job 9 30.</note> one of a thouſand. Nav, ſometimes<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſa. 14.3.</note> there's none that does me good, no not one. Though they have all<note n="(x)" place="margin">Joh 10.30.</note> one Father, and in truth, they and their Father are one; For my very life, I can't<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſal. 61.31.</note> truſt in them at all times, an leaſt not ſecurely; For ſome times, in my thirſt, they have given me<note n="(z)" place="margin">Joh 19.29.</note> vineger to drink, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions frightning me more, than the grace comforting. But oh my God, thou knoweſt, I wiſh I were<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat 25.43, 44</note> ſick, ſo they might viſit me: and in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110756:32"/>priſon, ſo they might but miniſter to me! for they have inſtructed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 4.3, 4.</note> and have ſtrengthened weak hands! They have upholdem him that was falling, and ſtrengthened feeble knees. Dying ſouls have ſet down under their ſhadow,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Can 2.3.</note> and their fruit has been ſweet to their taſte! From thy promiſes, oh my God, I have known thoſe who have<note n="(d)" place="margin">Can 5.1.</note> gathered myrrh, and ſpice; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and honey-comb, wine and milk, when they had been<note n="(c)" place="margin">Lam 3.15, 17.</note> filled with bitterneſs, and made drunk with wormwood: when their ſouls had been removed from peace, and they had forgot proſperitie!<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 30.6.</note> In my proſperitie I would ſay indeed, I ſhould never be moved, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently bid<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luk 12.19.</note> my ſoul, take more eaſe than now it dares, as having Goods laid up for many years; yea, for eternity, I would remove<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ec. 11.10.</note> ſorrow from my heart, could I but undoubtingly ſay of thy promiſes. That<note n="(i)" place="margin">Joh 17.4, 6, 10.</note> I have finiſhed the world they gave me to do! Could I but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110756:32"/>boldly tell thee, oh my God, That thine they were, and thou gaveſt them me; and all mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them! But alas, as oft as theſe are not my<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſal. 33.1, 2.</note> ſhield, my glory, and the lifter up of my head. Lord, how are they increaſed that trouble me; many are they that riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; many there be which ſay of my ſoul, There is no help for him in God. By night on<note n="(l)" place="margin">Can. 3.1.</note> my bed, when I ſeek the particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which I have choſe for my joy, when I ſeek them, and find them not: When<note n="(m)" place="margin">Can 5.6.</note> I open my heart to them, and they withdraw themſelves, and be gone, when<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pro. 1.28.</note> I ſeek them early too, and can't find them, though my coneeits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had been high,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Oba 1.3, 4.</note> though I had exalted my ſelf as the Eagle, and ſet my neſt among the Stars, how am I brought down in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menr? How are my<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.7.</note> lofty looks humbled, and my haughtineſs brought low? My own former
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110756:33"/>comforts<note n="(q)" place="margin">Job 30.10, 15.</note> abhor me: They flee from me, and ſpare not to ſpit in my face! Terrors are turned upon me, they purſue my ſoul as the wind, and my welfare paſſeth away as a cloud. For why? 'tis very true, in all thy Laws and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſal. 34.8.</note> I ſee the Lord is good, but 'tis in the promiſes, that I taſte and ſee; he is good, I can ſafely ſay, all thy words are ſweet, but 'tis of thy<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſa. 119.103.</note> promiſes, that I dare cry out, Oh how ſweet are thy words to my taſte: All their ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is laſting, not onely giving my ſoul a feaſt, but a continual one; and that a phyſical, not a diſeaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendring one. It doth good, and that like a medicine, it's honey pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as well as pleaſes. Were it ſweet<note n="(t)" place="margin">Job 20.12.</note> as ſin, only in the mouth, I could not give it a good word. Oh my God, the<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pro. 9.17.</note> ſtoln waters of it, which my heart in muſing takes ſecretly away; the bread of it, that I eat in ſecret places, I can't ſay, How ſweet they are;<note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Co 15.41.</note> there
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110756:33"/>is one glory of the Sun, another of the Moon, that gives light, and heat too, and life, this onely light. There is one glory of thy commanding word, that Moon rules in the night we are in, throughout our life, in this dark world. There is another glory of thy promiſing word, that Sun gives light and life to poor ſouls, and makes<note n="(y)" place="margin">2 Co 5.6.</note> us preſent with the Lord, even while we are abſent: And really<note n="(z)" place="margin">Mat 9.15.</note> the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Bride-chamber can t mourn, while in thy promiſes they have the Bridegroom with them. When they ſit at any time in the dark, and ſee no light; lo, thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes do make both<note n="(a)" place="margin">Joſh 10.12.</note> the Sun a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, to ſtand ſtill, upon their <hi>Gibeon;</hi> and the Moon in their val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of <hi>Ajalon,</hi> till the faces of their enemies are cloathed with<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſa. 83.16.</note> ſhame, and the crown of their faith flouriſheth on their own heads.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 2.20.</note> The <hi>Herods</hi> which ſeek the lives of my poor Infant-Graces and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, oh my God, they are never
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110756:34"/>ſtone dead. I can never ſay, They which ſought my childrens lives, are dead: No, they make, and I am ſure, they keep war<note n="(d)" place="margin">Rev 17.14.</note> with my Lambs. Thy very promiſes<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 46.9.</note> can't make their wars to ceaſe; but they can<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 68.30.</note> and do ſcatter them that delight in war? and that which they help me do, makes me ſay ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ex. 15.39.</note> The Lord is a Man of War. But, oh my God, my God, How to put on this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, 'tis rare that I can tell! Though thy promiſes be<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ro. 13.12.</note> armour of Light, yet ſure 'tis ſuch dazling light, that I can't tell how to wind and turn it. From whence it comes to paſs, that I am daily<note n="(i)" place="margin">Lev. 26.25.</note> deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over into the hands of ſin and ſorrow, doubt and fear, and all ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and didſt thou not, as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very dayes <hi>Emanuel,</hi> rid me out, and lead my<note n="(k)" place="margin">Re. 7.23.</note> captive, the ſorrows of hell would not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compaſs me, but ſwallow me up, and I ſhould be, not as my<note n="(l)" place="margin">1 Iſa 15.29.</note> Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was, rejected of men, and a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110756:34"/>man of ſorrows, but rejected of God,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Iſa. 53 3.</note> and a man of ſorrows. How oft, oh my God, do I hear that voice,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Luk 12.20.</note> This night thy ſoul ſhall be required of thee! How oft am I afraid, to<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pro. 6.4.</note> give ſleep to my eies, evenwhen I have much ado to keep it from them? How few nights in a week can I ſleep, as do<note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Th. 5.6.</note> athers? for they reſt from their labours, which I can't;<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſa. 40.12.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable evils compaſs me about, my iniquities take hold of me, ſo that I am not able to look up, or lye down! my conſcience it ſelf reviles me, ſaying,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſa. 42.3.</note> Where is now thy God? I am<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſa. 29.9.</note> dumb to my friends, becauſe they can't re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move my ſtroak: Nay, I live,<note n="(u)" place="margin">2 Co 6.10.</note> though as ſorrowful, yet as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes rejoycing, in my worſt fits, being ſure of this,<note n="(x)" place="margin">La. 3.</note> I am a living man. And 'tis meet for the<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 38.10.</note> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, to praiſe thee, not complain of thee. But, oh my God, my God, I pray thee for time to come, let that word of Truth, by which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110756:35"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Jam 1.18.</note> begat'ſt me, and of a ſtone dead imp, madeſt me a child to <hi>Abraham.</hi> Feed my<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Pe 2.2.</note> Babie graces and comforts with its ſincere milks, and be within me a word of Life. Amen, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="soliloquy">
            <head>
               <hi>8.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God, about his Threatnings.</head>
            <p>OH my God, I have thought, That 'tis not for indiſturbed Profeſſors,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pro. 31.4, 5, 6, 7.</note> to drink too much of the wine of the promiſes; and that leaſt they drink, and forget the Law, its direction and ob igation! I have judg'd the ſtrong drink of thy promiſes to belong to him, that is ready to periſh, and their wines, to them that are of feeble hearts, that they may drink, and not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, but redreſs their poverty by Chriſt's wealth, and conſider, That in him they ſhall feel their miſery no more. Now, thou knoweſt, I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110756:35"/>am one of that wretched number of men, who are ſetled on their lees, and that (too often) ſay,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Zep. 1.12.</note> The Lord will not do good,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Deu 24.19.</note> neither will he do evil! Oh my God, thou knoweſt, I have bleſt my ſelf in my heart, ſaying, I ſhall have peace, though I walk in the imagination of my heart! I have not been<note n="(e)" place="margin">Jer. 48.11.</note> emptied from veſſel to veſſel, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have I gone into the ſwift cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of the Goſpel: My taſte has remain'd in me, and my ſcent has not been chang'd, ſo ſetled have I been on my lees! Oh my God, I need, that word of thine, which is quick and powerful,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> ſharper than any two edged ſword, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit! I need ſome of its faithful<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pro. 27.6.</note> wounds, which will do me infinitely more good, than all the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pro. 28.23.</note> deceitful kiſſes. which my preſumption will never be able to faſten, on thy ſweeteſt promiſes! Oh correct me with them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them not from my ſoul; for if
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110756:36"/>thou beateſt me with them, I ſha not die! Whatever the minds of others are, Lord, thou ſhalt beat me with thy<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pro. 23.13, 14.</note> rod of threatnings, and deliver my ſoul from the hell of ſelf-liking, and ſelf-applauding. I dare not ſay to thy richeſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Job 6.22, 23.</note> bring unto me, or give me reward of your rich ſubſtance! or deliver me from the enemies hand, redeem me from the hand of the Almighty; without firſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy threatnings, O ye juſt ſtatutes, upon my hardneſs of heart, and all my wicked luſts,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. 11.6.</note> rain ye fire, brimſtone, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tempeſt! Bring upon them, that ſhut out my peace,<note n="(m)" place="margin">2 Pe 1.</note> a ſwift deſtruction; for I am ſure, before ſuch their deſtruction, the heart of man will be haughty! O Lord, without this paſſing through the fire of thy threatnings, I find, when I do my beſt, my hope is cut off, and my truſt is but<note n="(n)" place="margin">Job <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders web! Thy juſtice conſpicuous, in thy treats, being as needfull to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110756:36"/>keep me from preſumption, as the mercy in thy promiſes, to keep me from deſpair! Oh my God, I love thy book the better for thy threats, becauſe I find, they are the harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the promiſes, and Laws to the world. The world cries out,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Joh. 6.6.</note> They are hard ſayings, who can bear them? I eſteem them ſoft, and gentle, in every thing, ſaving their objects, to whom they are denounced; and they are<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ro. 2.5.</note> heart-hearted indeed. Thou, oh my God, their authour, art a God<note n="(q)" place="margin">Ex. 34.6.</note> of grace, thy end in giving them is<note n="(r)" place="margin">2 Ti. 1.9.</note> gracious; their effects on honeſt hearts, are graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but to the hard-hearted, all things are hard: It's true, they bruiſe but<note n="(s)" place="margin">Gen 3.15.</note> a ſinners heel, even while they bruiſe ſins head; if they do give us ſtripes, thoſe ſtripes are gifts, for with them, we are<note n="(t)" place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note> heal'd; they never cutting open any more than an orifice, for the oyl of thy promiſes to come in at! I know for the grace of the promiſes lips, and the<note n="(u)" place="margin">Can 1.2.</note> ſavour of their good
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110756:37"/>ointment, the virgins, fooliſh as well as wiſe, love them and follow them! But, oh my God, thou<note n="(x)" place="margin">Mat. 25.12.</note> knoweſt thy holy promiſes will not give that which is holy unto dogs, or dogged ſnarlers at thy righteous treats; they won't caſt their pearls unto ſwine!<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat 7.6, 7.</note> They may aſk, and conceit it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them; they may ſeek and fancy they find divine puri ie and peace, but a lie is in their right hand,<note n="(z)" place="margin">Eccl 4.12.</note> and their three fold cords of ignorance, errour, and pride are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily broken, ſometimes with mans, but ever with Gods judgement; which hath made me chuſe<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb 11.25.</note> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer the humiliations and breakings of thy threats, than to enjoy ſuch kind of pleaſures of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf, as are but for a ſeason. Oh my God, I find within me, that which is ſweetly drawn to thee, with the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Hoſ. 11.4.</note> cords of a man, and the bands of love: But I alſo find within me, that which were not<note n="(c)" place="margin">Jer. 23.19.</note> thy word. A hammer, it could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beat any good into me. If thou
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110756:37"/>onely<note n="(d)" place="margin">Can 1.5.</note> draweſt thy ſpiritual part with thy promiſes, it will run after thee! but my carnal part is not made willing to ſtoop, but in the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 110.</note> power of thy forcive Threats.<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mar 16.16.</note> He that believes ſhall be ſaved, will animate the Law of my mind; but 'tis he that believes not, ſhall be damn'd, that will break in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ro. 7.23.</note> the Law of my Members. I thank thee, oh my God, for ſuch<note n="(h)" place="margin">Zec 2.5.</note> a wall of Fire, round about my graces and duties! The Law is a defence, and the promiſes are<note n="(i)" place="margin">Eccl 7.12.</note> a defence againſt the weakneſs of Grace! But theſe Threats are the defence, againſt the ſtreng th of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: Ten Laws, and ten promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, won't<note n="(k)" place="margin">Deu 32.30.</note> chaſe a thouſand luſts; but Two of theſe will put ten thouſand to flight. Oh my God, Thy promiſes do lead many, but thy Threatnings<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Co 10.5.</note> drive every thought, to the obedience of thy Son,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Lu 19.27.</note> even thoſe that would not, that he ſhould reign over them. Theſe rods of iron, rule thoſe my
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110756:38"/>Rebels, whoſe<note n="(n)" place="margin">1 Sa 15.23.</note> rebellion is as the ſin of witchcraſt; they are the rod, which with the ſtaffe ef thy Laws and Promiſes, do exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſa. 23.4.</note> comfort me. If I ſay, That I (the chief of ſinners) have no ſin, I deceive my ſelf: and if I ſay, whilſt I have ſin,<note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Jo 1.8.</note> I am ſo whole, as not to need the Lancet of thy Threatnings, ſure the Truth is not in me.<note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Ti 3, 16.</note> All thy Scripture is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, I will never except the threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tning part.<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſal 19.9, 10, 11.</note> Thy judgements, <hi>David</hi> ſates, are to be deſired above gold, and are ſweeter than honey: By them, not onely thy enemies, but thy Friends are warn'd and in keeping them, as the apple of ones eies, there is great reward. Lord, I find this true of thy Threatnings, which as<note n="(s)" place="margin">Ro. 7.12.</note> thy Law are holy, juſt and good: and as<note n="(t)" place="margin">2 Pe 1.4.</note> thy promiſes are exceeding great and precious, and ſo let them ever be to my ſoul: <hi>Amen, Amen,</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:110756:38"/>
            <head>To my own SOUL.</head>
            <l>THE Horſe,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Job 39.19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25.</note> whoſe neck is cloath'd with very thunder,</l>
            <l>Whoſe noſthrils ſparkle fire,</l>
            <l>Hates valleys, would run higher; Counting it a wonder,</l>
            <l>That armed men, and fears themſelves affright</l>
            <l>His Rider, ſword, and ſpear, and ſhield,</l>
            <l>To him with fury ſteel'd,</l>
            <l>Are very play-games, he treads on ſo light:</l>
            <l>He cannot feel the ground</l>
            <l>He paws upon; and then the ſound,</l>
            <l>The Trumpets ſound exeites him more</l>
            <l>To ſcorn them, shan he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</l>
            <l>The thunder does but whiſtle in his ears,</l>
            <l>He noſes the Heaven it ſelf, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:110756:39"/>
Affected with the ſcent, and ſight of war,</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill he feels what its ſad iſſues are.</l>
            <l>Thus thou, my Soul, bearing</l>
            <l>Thy neck of braſs,</l>
            <l>Thy heart of Adamant;</l>
            <l>And the rocks none underſtand,</l>
            <l>Look'ſt Heaven in the face,</l>
            <l>While fire and brimſtone's raining down upon thee:</l>
            <l>Nor ſhakeſt thou at all,</l>
            <l>As if pride being thy wall,</l>
            <l>It could not make its threatned hell light on thee:</l>
            <l>Nay, (what's prodigious!) the more God's thundring Cannons roar</l>
            <l>To thee, deaf adder, thou the more by far, Slighteſt his war!</l>
            <l>God give thee ears to hear his Trumpet ſounds,</l>
            <l>They'l make thee haſte to Chriſt, his Blood, and Wounds.</l>
            <closer>
               <hi>Amen.</hi> So be it.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:110756:39"/>
            <head>10. A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God of worldly Friends.</head>
            <p>OH my God, (the greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the leſs)<note n="(t)" place="margin">See Rom. 8 31.</note> he that has the beſt Friend, has all friends. Methinks when he bids me<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pro 22.24.</note> make no friendſhip with an angry man, doth almoſt bid me, Make none with any man! For indeed, though<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eccl 7.11.</note> anger reſts not, ſave in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Fools, yet it finds too eaſie an impreſs into the boſome of<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pro. 15.1.</note> the Wiſeſt! Though thou my God beeſt<note n="(z)" place="margin">Joel 2.13.</note> ſlow to anger, they are few of thy ſervants who are ſo: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, That <hi>Solomon</hi> muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Dutie, what ſhould be; not of Certaintie, what is, when he ſaies, That<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pro. 17.17.</note> a friend loves at all times. Brethren,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Zec. 13.6.</note> there are, that one would think, were born for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity indeed; the giving it to us, not the taking us from it. Nay, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110756:40"/>(ſuch is the heighth of pride) few give their heartie friendſhip on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ther tearms, than what the common Saviour gives his upon; every fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſaying implicitly to us,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Joh 15.14.</note> Ye are my friends, if ye do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I command you! and if we won't make them our Gods, they'l make themſelves our Devils: if we ſhall<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſth 3.5, 6.</note> be <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s, they'l be <hi>Haman</hi>'s<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pro. 19.4.</note> Wealth, 'tis true, makes many friends; and when goods encreaſe, they are encreaſed, but 'tis to eat them; and when they are<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ecc 5.11.</note> eat up, many friends will not make wealth.<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat 11.5.</note> the poor ſhall have the Goſpel preach'd to them, and be turn'd off with a<note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Ti 4.8.</note> God will provide: but for any glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings out of the worldly friends charitie, they muſt not expect it, but ſit down, and content them with<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Ti. 6.6.</note> the gain of their own Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel! Godlineſs, which is indeed ſo<note n="(k)" place="margin">1 Ti 4.8, 18.</note> profitable to all things, that their friends unkindneſs is matter of pure notice, no reſent. Oh my
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110756:40"/>God, I have ſeen precious friends take much more joyfully<note n="(l)" place="margin">Heb. 10.34.</note> the ſpoiling of their friends, than the ſpending of a pittance of their goods. I have ſeen them in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſenſe,<note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Th 5.21.</note> hold faſt that which is good; and making what good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they have laid out, as fleeting<note n="(n)" place="margin">Hoſ. 6.4.</note> as <hi>Judah</hi>'s, a very morning cloud, and early dew. Sure if there be any faith in mortals, it is leſs than a very grain of muſtard ſeed, which is the<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat 13.33,</note> leaſt of all ſeeds, though when it's grown up into high profeſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt among herbs, and becomes a tree: ſo that ſilly deluded men, (haſtning to ſnares as very birds,) come build moſt ſtrange neſts, and lodge in the confidence of its bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. It ſeems from mens practices, to be of the ſame certaintie.<note n="(q)" place="margin">Ro. 3.4.</note> God is true, and that every man is a liar, and experience manifeſts it, That to truſt to man, is but to make<note n="(r)" place="margin">Iſa. 28.15.</note> lies our refuge, and<note n="(s)" place="margin">Jer. 13.25.</note> truſt in falſhood: For out of the<note n="(t)" place="margin">Jam. 3.10, 12</note> ſame
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110756:41"/>mouth proceedeth both bleſſing and curſing; and out of the ſame heart ſweet and bitter. Oh my God, when in diſtreſs one ſhall call aloud to his friend, (as<note n="(u)" place="margin">1 Ki 18.27, 29.</note> the <hi>Baaelites</hi> to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> (either he is taking a journey, or peradventure he ſleepeth, and muſt not be awaked: There's nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther voice, nor any to anſwer or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, if otherwiſe; yet the friend can't ſhut up the ſea of ſorrows<note n="(x)" place="margin">Job 38.8, 11, 31.</note> with doors, or ſay to ones calamitie, Hitherto ſhalt thou come, and no further; he cannot bind the ſweet influences of the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> or looſe the bonds of <hi>Orion.</hi> My friend is<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſal 23.1.</note> my ſhepherd, (my friend in Court) therefore I ſhall not want, is a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick in its argument unſound; in its experiment unſafe! No mortal<note n="(a)" place="margin">Can 4.4.</note> neck is like the tower of <hi>David,</hi> builded for an Armorie, hnng with<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſal 35 2.</note> Bucklers and Shields, againſt all aſſaults: Nay, there's none but what may need our help, while we ſeek its.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat 25.8.</note> If our lamps be gone out, it's vain to ſay to friends, Give
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110756:41"/>us of your oyl.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Joh. 3.27.</note> Chriſt ſaies, A man can receive nothing, except it be given him from Heaven; much leſs can he give any thing, except he receive it from heaven. Whence it came to paſs not unfrequently,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ro. 7.19, 17.</note> That as the evil our friends would not do us, that they do: So the good they would do us, that they do not; or if they do do it, it is no more they that do it, but God by them. Help me then, oh my God, and teach me for Jeſus ſake,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat 2.25.</note> to render to friends the things that are of friends; and unto thee, oh my God, the things that are thine. Make me know, that the fleſh of my friends is<note n="(f)" place="margin">Iſa. 40.6.</note> graſs, as well as other mens; and though their love comes up like a flower, it's obnoxious to be cut, or trod down like graſs,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat 6.30.</note> which to day is, and to morrow is caſt into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Be thou my friend, who chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt not, but loveſt to the end; yea, world without end,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Rev 2.10.</note> who art faithful to the Death, and giveſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110756:42"/>thy friends a crown of Life; whoſe love neither death can ſtrike,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ro: 3.38, 39</note> nor life conſume, nor angels ſtop in the way, nor principalities<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ro. 13.2.</note> and powers reſiſt to any, but their own damnation; nor things preſent croſs, nor things to come annoy, nor heighth pull down, nor depth ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up, nor any other creature do any other injury unto. Oh my God, make me know, men<note n="(l)" place="margin">Jam. 1.8.</note> are dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-winded, and their love is unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all its waies,<note n="(m)" place="margin">He. 12.15.</note> any root of bitterneſs may ſpring up, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it; the ruſt of money<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat 6.19.</note> may corrupt it; thieves may break in and ſteal it! An unbridled tongue may ride over it, and ſpoil it! Oh make me ſell all I have to get thy love; thy love which is an inheritance<note n="(o)" place="margin">1 Pe 1.4, 5.</note> incorruptible, undefiled, and that fades not away, reſerv'd in heaven, kept through my faith indeed, but by thy power, unto ſalvation! Make me know, good Lord, That all the friends on earth, can't make one<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat. 5.36.</note> hair of my head white or black; nor
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110756:42"/>by<note n="(q)" place="margin">Mat 6.27.</note> taking ever ſo much thought, add one cubit to my ſtature! when ſick or ſorrowful, there's not one to whom I can ſay,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 8.2, 7.</note> If thou wilt thou canſt make me clean and whole! nor can a ſoul of them ſay, I will come and heal thee.<note n="(s)" place="margin">Job 7.38.</note> But oh my God, he that believeth in thee, though he were dead, yet ſhould he live! Thou canſt<note n="(t)" place="margin">Ezo 37.6.</note> lay ſinews upon dry bones, cover them with fleſh, and breath in life! 'Tis but a word,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Heb 11.3.</note> and a world with thee!<note n="(x)" place="margin">Ecc 1.15.</note> that which is crooked, thou canſt make ſtrait; and that which is wanting, thou canſt number it. My God, my God, I beſeech thee put away my lovers and friends from me, and<note n="(y)" place="margin">Job 19.13.</note> let my acquaintance be eſtranged from that intimacie and perpetuitie of converſe with them, which hinders my communion with thee! Though of all things below, they are the ſweeteſt, they cannot<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pro 30, 8.</note> feed me with food convenient for me; though I am greatly prone to put<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pro. 25.19.</note> confidence in them, I
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110756:43"/>find that confidence in them in time of trouble, is like a broken tooth, and a foot out of joynt. Though they have<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eph 4.28.</note> ſtole away too too much of my affection already. Oh my God, let them ſteal no more! Enable me to<note n="(c)" place="margin">Luk 14.26.</note> hate my very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as much as is requiſite, to come a friend to thee! Be thou my whole acquaintance, and let me be ever with thee! either in delights, or deſires! Let me be a<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal 119.23.</note> compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all them that love thee; but let my communion be with, and my ſtrong confidence be in thee, who art never better known than truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! Amen, my God and Saviour, Amen, Amen!</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:110756:43"/>
            <head>10. A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God, of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</head>
            <p>BLeſſed God<note n="(x)" place="margin">Job 6.25.</note> how forcible are right words, thine I am ſure are Right, becauſe thine! and right forcible, becauſe they are ſuch<note n="(y)" place="margin">Jer. 23.29.</note> hammers as break the very Rocks of my heart! ſuch a fire as pierces into my inmoſt depths, and reaches the droſs,<note n="(z)" place="margin">1 Co 2.9.</note> which no Eye hath ſeen, or ear heard. Such Monitors, as whoever won't hear,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Luk 16.31.</note> would not believe, if one came from the dead! Such as<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.9.</note> cleanſe the ways of even young men themſelves, ſo hard to be reclaimed, that <hi>David</hi> cries out aſtoniſhedly, Wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſhall a man young, cleanſe his waies! Of very ſtocks and ſtones, thy word<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 3.9.</note> has rais'd up children to <hi>Abraham!</hi> It is<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 43.1.</note> the arm of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110756:44"/>God; yea, and very ſword too! God the Father's arm, God the Son's<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Co 4.20.</note> power, God the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Eph 6.17.</note> Spirits ſword! Oh my God,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pre. 15.23.</note> words ſpoken in ſeaſon, how good are they? but when are thine out of ſeaſon? When<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Pe 2.2.</note> we are babes, they are milk,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pro 16.24.</note> ſweet and nouriſhing! When grown, they are ſtrong meat, making us go in thy wayes without wearineſs; yea,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſal. 19.5.</note> run without fainting; when in bitterneſs of ſin and ſorrow, they are honey, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and purgative too! When in doubts, they are Counſellors! when fainting,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Can 2.5.</note> they are flagons of ſoul-reviving cordials, and apples of comfort! When quite dead, and the ſpirit gone,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Jo. 6.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the words which thou ſayeſt, they are ſpirit, and they are life.<note n="(n)" place="margin">Jam 1.18.</note> We are begotten by thy holy word,<note n="(o)" place="margin">pſa. 119.93</note> as many as are born of God! We are fed by the ſame, and no better fed than taught nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. O my God, there is not a<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſa. 119 105.</note> word in my tongue, but thou knoweſt it altogether. Oh would
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110756:44"/>to Chriſt, there may not be a<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſal. 139.4.</note> word in thy Book, but I may know it altogether.<note n="(r)" place="margin">Jam 1.5.</note> Praiſed be thy holy Name, thou doſt not ſay; If any man want wiſdom, that then he ſhall ſtrait be damn'd for a fool; but ſayeſt, That then he ſhould aſk it of thee! Lord, I aſk of thee that<note n="(s)" place="margin">2 Ti. 3.15.</note> wiſedom to ſalvation, which thy word alone is able to give me. I obſerve, That all worldly wiſe withour this, are<note n="(t)" place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> as harmleſs as ſerpents; as wiſe as doves without hearts: they are wiſe to do evil in the form of godlineſs, but to do good as good, they have<note n="(u)" place="margin">Jer. 4.22.</note> none; the leaſt knowledge. What are all humane Authors, that I ſhould take knowledge<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſal. 144.3.</note> of them? Or the moſt Learned, that I ſhould make account of them?<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 55.8, 9.</note> Their words are not as thy words; nor their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as thy notions! As the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are high above the earth: ſo are thy words high above their words; &amp; thy notions above theirs! Methinks of all the Books in my
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110756:45"/>Studie, it is my Bible onely which can uſe the mighty Lords own words.<note n="(z)" place="margin">Iſa. 45.22.</note> Look unto me, and be ye ſaved! All the ends of the earth,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pro. 8.18, 20, 21, 14.</note> riches and honour are with me; yea, durable riches and honours lead in the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, in the midſt of the paths of Judgement. That I may cauſe thoſe that love me to inherit ſubſtance, and I will fill their treaſures! Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel is mine, and ſound wiſedom; I am underſtanding, I have ſtrength. Other Books, I confeſs, with their much<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pro. 7.21.</note> fair ſpeech, do cauſe me to yield, with the flattering of their lips they force me: But when they draw me from thy Book, oh my Book, I find my going after them, is juſt a meer oxes going to the ſlaughter, and a fools to the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſtocks. Other books<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pro. 25.14.</note> boaſt in Title pages, of falſe gifts, and are meer clouds, and wind without rain; but thine gives good and<note n="(d)" place="margin">Jam 1.17.</note> perfect gifts, coming down from the Father of lights.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pro. 23.35.</note> They
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110756:45"/>have ſtricken me with reproofs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was not ſick; they have beaten me with inculked rebukes, and my conſcience felt it not; but in thy word, the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mar. 26.75.</note> Cocks crow ſo loud, that they will make one go out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luk 22, 62.</note> and weep bitterly, that one can go out no further. The word<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mal. 3.2.</note> is a Refiners fire, and ſuffers ſome cleanſing inſide and out! Theirs maketh Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, painted ſepulchres, but no<note n="(i)" place="margin">Joh. 1.49.</note> true Iſraelites, in whom there is no guile;<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iſa. 5.12.</note> the harp and the viol are in their feaſts, the tabret and pipe of the excellency of mans wiſedom, pleaſing words, and tinkling cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals. But thy Book gives<note n="(l)" place="margin">Can. 15.1.</note> the myrrh with ſpice; the honey with the honey-comb; the wine with milk. Oh my God, thou haſt made great<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſal 136.8, 9.</note> lights in thy word, the Sun, the Moon, the Stars, of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, promiſes, and providences; elſe would this world be<note n="(n)" place="margin">Joh 10.21, 22</note> a land of darkneſs, and the ſhadow of death: A land of darkneſs, as hells
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110756:46"/>darkneſs it ſelf, of the ſhadow of death, without any order, and where the light would be as dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Some deal with thy word, as<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ru. 1.14, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Orpah</hi> with <hi>Naomi,</hi> go ſome part of the way with her, kiſs her, and then leave her. But oh! may my ſoul (as <hi>Ruth</hi>'s) cleave to it, and for ever ſay, Whither thou goeſt, I will go; where thou lodgeſt, I will lodge; thy wayes ſhall be my wayes, and thy God ſhall be my God.<note n="(p)" place="margin">pſal. 145.10, 11, 12, 14, 15.</note> All thy works do praiſe thee, O Lord, and thy Saints do bleſs thee! they ſpeak ſweetly of the glory of thy Kingdom, and talk of thy power; but 'tis thy word makes known to the ſons of men, thy mighty Acts of Creation and Redemption, and the glorious Majeſty of thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom! 'Tis thy word upholds all them that fall; and raiſes up thoſe that be bowed down! Out of thy word thou giveſt the beſt meat to them, whoſe eyes wait upon thee. Thy gracious providences often make me cry out,<note n="(q)" place="margin">pſal. 136.1, 10, 15, 16,</note> O give thanks
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:110756:46"/>to the Lord, for he is good! But 'tis thy Word onely makes me add, His mercy endureth for ever. For why? 'Tis by thy Word that thou ſmiteſt <hi>Aegyptian</hi> luſts in their firſt-born! and overthroweſt reigning ſins, and their hoſts of ſnares and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in the Sea of thy grace, red with the Bloud Royal of thy Son! 'Tis by thy Word thou leadeſt thy people through the valley of ſin ond ſorrow, into the heavenly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan!</hi> 'Tis thy Word, that in the wilderneſs of this world,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſa. 105.41</note> opens very rocks that waters guſh out! yea,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſal. 107.35</note> that turns my part of this wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs into a ſtanding pool of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; and my dry ground into wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſprings.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:110756:47"/>
            <head>
               <hi>11.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with the Soul, about its ſloth.</head>
            <p>O My ſoul! my ſoul!<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pro. 2.6, 16.</note> 'Tis in thy own conceit, That ſuch a ſluggard as thou, is wiſer than ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven men, that can render a reaſon. Doſt think it enough, as<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 9.20.</note> the woman with the bloody Flux, only to come behind Chriſt, and touch the hem of his garment? Hers was a Flux of Blood; thine of ſuch ſins, as made a Flux of Chriſts Blood! Her diſeaſe but of Twelve years, thine of almoſt twice twelve, for thou waſt conceiv'd in it!<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat 9.21.</note> As ſhe ſaid of Chriſt, dareſt thou ſay of Chriſtian Religion; If I may but touch its garment, I ſhall be whole? If not, why ſtandeſt thou idle? hath not God ſent thee to hotter work.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mar. 6.8, 9, 7.</note> Is this like a Diſciple of Chriſt, to be projecting for ſcrip, bread, money in thy purſe, and two coats?
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110756:47"/>and not be caring for power of thy unclean ſpirit, and being ſhod with the ſandals of the Goſpel? Art thou my ſoul, the <hi>Bethlehem</hi> wherein Chriſt is born? or the <hi>Sodom</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in pride, idleneſs, and fulneſs of bread reigns?<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pro 21.25.</note> The deſire of the ſlothful Chriſtian to be ſaved, damns him, becauſe his hands refuſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in the work of the Lord.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 19.20.</note> All theſe things have I kept from my youth up, was the word of an hypoorite, and very likely an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate! 'Tis another diligence<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Pe 1.10.</note> enſures Election, and ſecures from falling? Be not<note n="(g)" place="margin">Jam 1.22. Jam. 1.21.</note> deceiv'd, oh my ſoul, with vain words! It is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian onely, that undoes not himſelf! A mans own words are not (as God's) able to ſave his ſoul! Salvation muſt be<note n="(h)" place="margin">Phil 2.12.</note> work'd, not talk'd out! Examine thy ſelf, prove thy ſelf, oh my ſoul! for knoweſt thou not, that great induſtry is in thee,<note n="(i)" place="margin">2 Go 13.5.</note> except thou beeſt a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate! Not to do well, or<note n="(k)" place="margin">Gal 6.</note> to be weary of well doing, is a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110756:48"/>token of God's being weary of thee, and thy being ſo of him! and every ſuch<note n="(l)" place="margin">Heb. 10.38.</note> drawing back, final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſiſted in, is to perdition! 'Tell not me there is a lion, or ſingularity in the way; a lion of cenſoriouſneſs in the ſtreets, I ſhall be bit! Thou muſt be ſo, but who can help it? If Chriſt<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mal 10, 16, 25.</note> will ſend forth his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in the midſt of lions and wolves, 'tis ſo much the better for you, if you are bit ſoundly, you will be the more like your Maſter!<note n="(n)" place="margin">Heb 10.</note> The ſacrifice of thy fame, the offering, the burnt-offering of it, on this account, is ſuch as God will not deſpiſe! but has pleaſure in: Men indeed, and of repute, for pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, too many won't endure<note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Ti 4.3.</note> ſound doctrine! much leſs convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing converſation! But God will have us do more<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat 5.47.</note> than others, either do, or allow us to do! Oh my ſoul, look right before thee, Were it not better that men ſhould ſay to thee and thy graces, Why do ye more than others, by way of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110756:48"/>than that Chriſt, when he comes, ſhould ſay, What do ye more than others, by way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. Chriſt,<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat 7.29.</hi> Read the four Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts.</note> thy Doctor, teaches not as the Scribes, but as one having authority, Don't thou live as the Scribes, but as one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving activity! Chriſt thy Saviour did and ſuffered nothing, but mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles for thee, double miracles, to wit, becauſe he did them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did them for thee! and wilt thou ſtick to do more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for him! Hear, oh my ſoul! not meerly<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat 9.13.</note> the whole in ſin, but the ſick in grace, do need the phyſician! For Jeſus came not onely that his ſouls ſhould have life, but that they<note n="(s)" place="margin">Joh. 10.10.</note> ſhould have it more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly! If thou art not purged to bring forth more fruit, 'tis dubious whether thou art yet ingrafted in him,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Joh. 15.2.</note> or beareſt any! <hi>David</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently ſayes, God's right<note n="(u)" place="margin">See Pſal. 63 8.</note> hand upheld him! but when was that, not when he ran from God; no, nor when he ſate ſtill neither; no,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110756:49"/>nor when he followed God ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily neither, but when his very ſoul followed hard after God. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pro 1.16.</note> That the feet of ſome run to evil. 'Tis pity that good ſhould be gone unto a ſlower pace; and know thou my ſoul, If hell be moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.32. Can. 1.4 Heb. 12.1.</note> run unto, 'tis a ſhame but to go to heaven! and thou waſt beſt look to it too; for I miſtake, if there be any way to heaven, beſides<note n="(z)" place="margin">See 1 Cor. 9.24.</note> the Race one! in which it ſelf, be confident, every Runniug won't obtain! Beware of a falſe gallop. Methinks S. <hi>Peter</hi> makes<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Pe 1.8.</note> aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in grace, and daily addition, the onely ſecurity againſt ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. St. <hi>Paul</hi> contends for<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Co 8.7.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in every particular grace, I am ſure one degree of abounding would not ſerve his turn neither; Abound<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Th. 4.1.</note> ſayes he) more and more; nay, and he was for<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Co 15.58.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding alwayes too: Youth and old age, proſperity and adverſity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſtill abound. And really all but need, ſith now I remember it, what
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110756:49"/>ever a man hath, and abounds not in, goes for nothing with him who is to be our Judge. From him<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 25, 29.</note> ſaith he) that hath not, ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away even that which he hath. If ſo, as<note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Ti 5.17.</note> the Elders muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in the word and Doctrine, I proteſt thou and thy neighbours were beſt labour hard, in the word and practice of it. 'Tis true, they<note n="(g)" place="margin">Re. 14.13.</note> who do reſt from their religious labours, have their works follow them; but if they don't follow them too, and caſt them at the bar of God, far from that reſt. Say not, oh my ſoul, the wind blows in thy face, ſet heavenward! 'Tis onely a<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pro. 20.4.</note> ſluggard, that will not plow, by reaſon of the cold! He that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the wind (of any oppoſition) well he may ſcatter, he will never ſow, in the whole ſeed-time of grace: and he that does but ſo much<note n="(i)" place="margin">Eccl 11.4, Pro. 20.4,</note> as regard the clouds, that drop down ſcuds of temporal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, he may dream of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the harveſt of glory; but
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110756:50"/>there he may be, and have nothing; no, not a drop it ſelf to cool his tongue. I tell thee, oh my ſoul, hindrances of thy pious diligence, numberleſs thou maiſt make, not one canſt thou find made to thy hand. Thou lieſt, when thou ſaieſt,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pro. 22.13.</note> There's a lion in the way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out! The lion that will bite thee, I mean, for why?<note n="(l)" place="margin">1 Pet 5.8.</note> Satan is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that if but reſiſted faithfully, will not bite thee at all, unleſs his flight, and leaving thee to ſin alone, will bite thee! The lion, if any be, is in the den of thy brutiſh ſluggiſh heart, whoſe luſts, indeed, are roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lions, ever ſeeking what graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous motions they may devour! No man ſtands idle, but he who ſtands for idleneſs; and I may boldly ſay it (as of every wicked Agent, ſo) of every one wickedly inactive, (who<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ro. 9.19.</note> hath reſiſted his will? Even we poor potſheards, have<note n="(n)" place="margin">Ro. 9.21.</note> power over the dab of clay, call'd our ſelves, to make freely one acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto the honour, and another to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110756:50"/>the diſhonour of our Chriſtian names! God gives us, would we but give our ſelves<note n="(o)" place="margin">Phi 2.13.</note> to will, and to do: We have his, could we get but our own good pleaſure.<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pro. 19.15.</note> The deep ſleep, in which we can't work, 'tis ſlothfulneſs caſts us into that; the<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pro. 15.19.</note> nettles and thorns that make irkſom our work, are alſo its product. Oh my ſoul, let not idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pro. 24.30, 31.</note> hinge thee on thy bed, and give thy hand to thy boſome,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pro 26.14, 15.</note> and then thou ſhalt find it no more grievous, to ſet thy hand to God's plow, than to put it to thy mouth, even with thy neceſſary food. Methinks the Authour of the Epiſtle to the<note n="(t)" place="margin">See Heb. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Hebrews,</hi> makes Believers and ſlothful Profeſſors no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing a kin, his But is ſo adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; and I proteſt, 'tis enough to make thy betters in ſacred induſtry ſhake again, to once Con <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Obſervation. Slothfulneſs not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuſes the materials of one that is going<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ecc 10.18.</note> to build, but it even decayes that which is ever ſo well
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110756:51"/>built up already; Nay, and though it be built, ay, and poſſeſſed too; though it bea houſe, a furniſh'd houſe, yet idleneſs will make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenantable! My ſoul, my ſoul I though thou wert built up; ay, and Chriſt inhabited thee; thou muſt not lend, but give; not ſome, but all diligence to ſecure his Houſe, and Hold.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="soliloquy">
            <head>12. <hi>A</hi> Soliloquy <hi>with Pride.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OH pride, pride!<note n="(x)" place="margin">Job 9.30, 31</note> If I maſh my ſelf with ſnow water, and make my hands never ſo clean, yet doſt thou plunge me in the ditch, and make my own clothes to abhor me!<note n="(y)" place="margin">Hoſ. 13.8.</note> Thou meeteſt every gift and grace I have, as a Bear that is bereft of her whelps, and doſt rent the very caul of their hearts.<note n="(z)" place="margin">Ge. 49.7.</note> Curſed be thy anger, for it is fierce;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110756:51"/>and thy wrath, for it is cruel! Thou haſt ſmitten all God's friends on the cheek-bone, nor art thou<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſa. 3.6, 7.</note> afraid of ten thouſand of Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, which have ſet themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound thee! Who<note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 41.2, 14 21, 26, 28, 29, 33.</note> can put an hook into thy noſe? or bore thy jaw through with a thorn? Who can open the doors of thy face? thy teeth are terrible round about? Thy breath kindles coals, and a flame goes out at thy mouth! The word of God, that layes at thee, cannot hold! the ſpear, the dart, for the Habergion! God's arrows make thee not fly, thou counteſt his darts as ſtubble! Upon earth here is not thy like, thou art made without fear.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 55.21.</note> Thy words are ſmoother than butter, but war is in thy heart! They are ſofter than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yl, yet are they drawn ſwords! Thy voice, oh pride, is<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ge. 27.22.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi>'s voice, but thy hands are the hands of <hi>Eſau.</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Job 13.7.</note> If thou doſt ſpeak for God, 'tis wickedly! and if thou doſt talk for him, 'tis deceitfully; as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110756:52"/>
               <hi>Job</hi> ſaid of his friends.<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſa. 45.8.</note> All thy garments ſmell of myrrh, aloes and Caſſia! but they are fearfully<note n="(g)" place="margin">Jude 23.</note> ſpotted by the fleſh, if look'd into! Gifts, which are<note n="(h)" place="margin">Job 1 14, 15</note> thy oxen, thou keepeſt ever plowing; luſts, which are thy aſſes, thou kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt feeding, till the righteous God ſend his Executioners of Juſtice, to take both, and ſlay them, with the ſword of vengeance.<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ti 6.6.</note> Thy god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is no gain, nor is it profitable to any thing<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Ti 3.5.</note> with its form, but to gnaw out the heart of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Heb. 5.7.</note> The ſtrongeſt cries of thy prayers are but idle clamorouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſtark ſin; it's<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſal 109.7.</note> ſtrength is juſt as its length, but for a<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat. 23.14.</note> pretence!<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mat. 21.13.</note> Thy Houſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers is but a Den of thieves, lying in wait for the curſe of being well ſpoken of by all men!<note n="(p)" place="margin">Jam 2.18.</note> Thou ſheweſt thy faith by thy works! I'le ſay it is a faith of miracles, which<note n="(q)" place="margin">Mat. 17.20.</note> if one have of it no more than a grain of muſtard ſeed, one ſhall throw away mountains of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110756:52"/>convictions of God on ones ſoul.<note n="(r)" place="margin">Heb. 11.33.</note> 'Tis a faith that ſubdues King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes indeed! For I call God to witneſs, it ſubdues the Kingdom of Chriſt<note n="(s)" place="margin">Ro. 14.23.</note> in the Goſpel.<note n="(t)" place="margin">Luk. 7.50.</note> 'Tis a faith, that whatever is of it is ſin: Tis a ſaving faith with the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; for I confeſs, it ſaves it ſelf, though it<note n="(u)" place="margin">1 Ti 1.19.</note> make Shipwrack of a good Conſcience!<note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Jo 4.28.</note> Thy love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pride is ſo perfect, that it caſts out all fear of the Lord!<note n="(y)" place="margin">Exo. 20.</note> and ſhewes kindneſs to thouſands of thoſe both men and things, which love thee, and keep thy Commands! But 'tis true, for Gods Statutes, which are thy<note n="(z)" place="margin">Mat 5.44.</note> enemies; thou canſt not love them: and for Gods Attributes, which deſpitefully uſe thee, thou canſt not pray for them. Thou doſt indeed, oh Pride<note n="(a)" place="margin">Col. 3.2.</note> ſet thy Affections on thoſe things which are above, and (to uſe thy own hearts dialect.)<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 113.6.</note> thou doſt humble thy ſelf, to behold the things that are done in heaven! But, having ſaid in thy heart, That<note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſa. 45.22.</note>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:110756:53"/>Thou art God, and there is non beſide thee; 'tis the plaineſt thing of ten thouſand,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 53.3.</note> that every of thy affections is gone back to thy ſelf, they are altogether become filthy, there is none that doeth good, no not one.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſa. 57.4.</note> Their poiſon is like the poiſon of a ſerpent, and they are deaf adders. Let God<note n="(f)" place="margin">Job 2.11.</note> but touch their bone or their fleſh, they will curſe him to his face.<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ex. 1.12.</note> And the more they ſhall be afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the more they will grow. Let Religion aſk them for water, they will<note n="(h)" place="margin">Jud 5.25. 26, 27.</note> give her milk, and butter promiſes in gay profeſſions; but they will put their hands to the mail and their right hands to the devils hammer; with the hammer they will ſmite piety, and ſmite off its head; when they have pierced through its Temples!<note n="(i)" place="margin">Job 10.14, 12, 13.</note> They break down godlineſs with breach upon breach; and ruſh upon it as a Gyant, they take it by the neck, and ſhake it to pieces, and ſet it up for their mark. Oh pride, I do not wonder that God
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110756:53"/>hates even the very<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pro 6.17.</note> look of thee! For I am ſure, thou and all thy fathers houſe, do hate God with a<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal 139.</note> perfect hatred, &amp; count him your enemy! Thy natural lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Eze 21.26, 27.</note> Remove God's dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, take off his Crown, overturn, overturn, overturn him! I have ſworn by my ſelf, that unto me eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry knee ſhall bow. Oh pride, pride!<note n="(n)" place="margin">Jer. 13.27.</note> I have ſeen thine Idolatries, thy Adulteries, and thy Neighings; the lewdneſs of thy ſpiritual whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and all thy abominations.<note n="(o)" place="margin">Hab. 2.16.</note> The cup of the Lords right hand be turn'd upon thee, and a ſhameful ſpewing be on all thy glory, in my heart and life!<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 17, 18, 24.</note> The Lord ſmite the crown of thy head with a ſcab, and diſcover thy ſeeret parts! The Lord take away the braverie of thy tinkling ornaments! In ſtead of thy ſweet ſmells, let there be in my ſoul the ſtink of my own corruption! In ſtead of thy girdles, a being rent and broken in ſpirit! In ſtead of thy well ſet hair, baldneſs! In ſtead
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:110756:54"/>of thy ſtomachers, a girding of ſackcloth, and burning by the<note n="(q)" place="margin">Heb 11.34.</note> fire of his ſpirit, In ſtead of thy beauty! How joyfully could I take the ſpoiling of rhy Goods! Have thy<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 5.29, 40.</note> right eyes bor'd out, and thy right hands cut off! and not onely have thy cloak, but thy coat alſo took away! God fire out thy<note n="(s)" place="margin">Lu. 9.58.</note> Foxes out of their holes, and thy unclean birds out of their neſts, that the Son of Man, and Saviour of men, may have where to lay his head, within my<note n="(t)" place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> heart! May thy Sun, thy Moon, and thy ſtars be darkned.<note n="(u)" place="margin">Eccl 12.2, 3, 6, 1.</note> May the keepers of thy Houſe Tremble, and thy ſtrong men bow themſelves, may thy ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cords be looſed, and thy golden bowls be broken; may evil dayes come on thee, and ſuch wherein my Soul may ſay, I have no pleaſure in thee.<note n="(x)" place="margin">Job 4.9.</note> By the blaſt of God, mayſt thou periſh, by the breath of his noſthrils maiſt thou be conſum'd<note n="(y)" place="margin">Rev 2.13.</note> I know thy works, and where thou dwelleſt, even where <hi>Satans</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:110756:54"/>ſeat is, in the hearts and manners of men! I know thou<note n="(z)" place="margin">2 Pe 2.1.</note> bringeſt in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought me! Thou<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 13.9.</note> carrieſt men away with divers and ſtrange doctrines; thou makeſt the morality of the earth,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Jam 3.15.</note> earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſenſual, diveliſh. Curſed be the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Luk 11.27.</note> womb that bare thee, and the paps that gave thee ſuck.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 137.9.</note> Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſhall he be that taketh and daſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thy little ones againſt the ſtones!<note n="(e)" place="margin">Job 20.9.</note> May the eye of God, which hath ſeen thee in my heart &amp; ways, never ſee thee more, nor thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces know thee any more! Maieſt thou, oh pride,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 132.18.</note> be clothed with ſhame; and upon all the graces of God, that are thy enemies, may the Crown flouriſh, ſo even ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſal. 130.6.</note> My ſoul ſhall wait for the Lord, more than they that watch for the morning; I ſay, more than they that watch for the morning! Amen, Amen, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:110756:55"/>
            <head>
               <hi>13.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with the ſoul about Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</head>
            <p>MY ſoul, my ſoul! It is ſaid<note n="(h)" place="margin">Eccl 6.7.</note> All the labour of man is for his mouth. But who had thought, this could have been true of his religious labour? For really, though<note n="(i)" place="margin">Joſh. 1.8.</note> the Law ought not to depart out of a man's mouth; ſo neither ought it to enter in, ſave<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 12.34.</note> out of the hearts abundance. <hi>Eliphaz</hi> adviſes<note n="(l)" place="margin">Job 22.22.</note> 
               <hi>Job,</hi> to lay up God's word in his heart, not his mouth:<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pro 3.1. Prov. 4.23.</note> and <hi>Solomon</hi> thought no cabinet ſo proper to keep divine Commands in, as it: Nay, God himſelf chuſes the Tables of the heart,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Jer. 31.33.</note> for to write his Laws in; which makes me conclude, A man may keep his mouth and tongue richly, and yet never keep<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pro. 21.23.</note> his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:110756:55"/>ſoul from troubles: and this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know, whatever entreth in at the mouth, (if it find no place in the heart) it goes into<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat 15.18.</note> the belly of hidden luſts, and is caſt out into their draught. The things of God which proceed out of the mouth, when they proceed not forth out of the heart, they defile the man. So little a praiſe is it, to be a man of pure lips, if no more; and eſpecially if that of the<note n="(q)" place="margin">Iſa. 29.</note> wiſe man be true, to wit, that though<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pro. 14.23.</note> in all labour there be profit, yet lip labour has a direct tendency to povertie! Oh my ſoul!<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pro. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> tells thee, That the Hypocrite with his mouth deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his neighbour. I tell thee more, even that he deſtroys himſelf: for though he has<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pro. 7.14, 9, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> Peace offerings with him, and every day payes his vows; yet he goes forth, in the black and dark angels of his ſoul, to meet the Devil, diligently to find him, though he decks his bed with covering of religious Tape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:110756:56"/>with carved works and fine li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen of profeſſion, though he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes his bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinamon; yet he takes his fill of ſpiritual whoredom, and ſolaces himſelf with atheiſtical loves, while the good conſcience is not at home, but is turn'd out of doors with a bag of money, not to come home till the day appointed, even that of Death and Judgement! If of any ſoul alive, this, oh my ſoul, is true of the hypocritical one, He feedeth on aſhes, a deceiv'd heart hath turn'd him aſide, that he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his ſoul, nor ſay,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iſa. 44.20.</note> Is there not a lye in my right hand.<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pro 12.15.</note> For the way of ſuch a fool is right in his own eyes: And Chriſt himſelf does not deny, but he has his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 6.2. Mat. 6.4 Mat.6.7 Mat. 6.6 Mar. 6.31, 32,</note> He does his alms to the devil in ſecret; and that father of his, who ſeeth him in ſecret, himſelf rewards him openly! Though when he prayes to God, he uſes as vain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions as the Heathens do; yet when he prayes to the devil, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110756:56"/>wiſhes for deviliſh things, he keeps in the cloſet of privacy, and ſhuts all the doors, at which men may ſee in. He takes no thought, ſaving, What ſhall I do to eat Chriſt's fleſh, or drink his blood, or cloath me with the garment of his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. (For after all theſe things do true Iſraelites ſeek) but he ſeeks firſt the titular Kingdom of God, and the profeſſional Righteouſneſs thereof, and thinks all theſe things ſhall be added. He takes no care for to morrow, but lets that care for it ſelf! Sufficient he thinks, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Day of Judgement, if to any day, is the evil thereof. His love, I can't ſay, is without diſſimulation, but ſure<note n="(z)" place="margin">Mat 5.44.</note> love he does his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, God's Lawes; bleſs he does them, though they curſe him; and pray for God's promiſes, though they deſpightfully uſe him, and give him no one drop of comfort! He's even almoſtas perfect as his father, which is inHell, is perfect. This indeed, oh my ſoul!<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat 7.11, 9, 10, 9, 10.</note> I obſerve;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110756:57"/>that being evil, the hypocrite knows how to give good gifts: and though when his friend aſks of him for bread, what he gives him, in reſpect of himſelf, be no more than a ſtone, and he takes no more in it; yet to his friend 'tis good bread. Though the Truths he delivers, be to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſerpents, that ſometimes ſting his ſoul, yet, as he delivers them, they are fiſh. What is<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Co 4.2.</note> handling the Word of God deceitfully, if this be not? to wit, Taking it<note n="(c)" place="margin">Deu 30.14.</note> very nigh one, even into ones mouth, and yet not ſo much as know it, any otherwiſe than God knows the proud, to wit,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal 138.6.</note> afar off; to be not a hearer onely, but a talker too, and yet not a<note n="(e)" place="margin">Jam 1.22.</note> doer of the Word; to do with it many wonderful works, by it to<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat 7.22.</note> caſt out devils, and nevertheleſs (as the Phariſees and Scribes)<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mar 7.13.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that of none effect to ones ſelf. Oh my ſoul! for the love of God let not the Word of God<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſa 119.103</note> be ſweet to thy mouth, and not to thy
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:110756:57"/>taſt!<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Th 5, 26.</note> Kiſs it with no <hi>Judas</hi>-like but with a holy kiſs.<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat 13.57.</note> As 'tis ſaid of a prophet, he is not without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſave in his own countrey: ſo may it be ſaid of the Word, it is not without honour, ſave in its own proper Region, that of the heart.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Deu 4.9.</note> Oh keep thy heart and it, more dear than thy hearts blood, with all diligence;<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſa 45.1.</note> Let thy heart en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite good matters of it.<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pro 15.13. Pro. 15.15.</note> A mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart makes a chearful counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance! Let thy hearts mirth in it, be that which ſets thy chearful countenance on it! 'Tis a heart, a heart, a heart I tell thee, a merry heart with it, which hath a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Feaſt for the Lord, and from the Lord. In the Word, God opens his heart; to the Word, open thy heart, even the hidden man of thy heart. Oh my ſoul,<note n="(o)" place="margin">1 pe 3.4.</note> I charge thee before God, who has quickned thee, and before Jeſus Chriſt, who never made or will endure rotten profeſſions; that thou take not the oyl<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſa. 104.15</note> of the Word, to make thy
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:110756:58"/>face to ſhine without the wine of the Word, to make thy very heart glad in the Lord.<note n="(r)" place="margin">Jam 3.5.</note> The tongue is a little member, don't think that God intended it for the Seat and Dwelling houſe of his great Law.<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pro. 16.1.</note> The anſwer of the tongue, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed from the Lord, but when? When the preparations of the heart in man, be ſo to<note n="(t)" place="margin">pro. 15.7.</note> the tongue, is the diſpenſer, and ſhould be the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſer of holy knowledge! But the heart, my ſoul, the heart 'tis, that has the good<note n="(u)" place="margin">Mat 6.21.</note> treaſure; and as 'tis true, where the treaſure is, there the heart will be: ſo really, where the heart is, there the<note n="(x)" place="margin">Mat 12.35.</note> treaſure will be, good or bad. O my ſoul, better is a little in the heart,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pro. 15.16.</note> with the fear of the Lord, than great treaſure of God's word in thy mouth, and the trouble of thy tongue therewith. He,<note n="(z)" place="margin">Heb 11.4.</note> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, yet ſpeaks of ſpiritual life, is infinitely far from that ſpeech, which<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ca. 411.</note> Chriſt Jeſus calls comely; and yet, if he were not, the wiſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110756:58"/>man tells us, Excellent ſpeech<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pro. 17.7.</note> becomes not a fool. O my ſoul, my ſoul! Take thou<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat 10.19.</note> then no thought, how or what thou ſhalt ſpeak of God, or his wayes,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat 12.35.</note> but out of the good treaſure of thy heart. Let it ever be given unto thee, what thou ſhalt ſay.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mal. 2.6.</note> Let the Law of Truth be in thy lips,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 15.2.</note> and ſpeak the truth in thine heart. The way to be without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, is to be ſincere, and make clean the inſides of the veſſels,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Phil 1.10.</note> the Kingdom of God is not in word!</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:110756:59"/>
            <head>
               <hi>14.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God, complaining of vile Affections.</head>
            <p>OH my God, my God!<note n="(h)" place="margin">Job 19.23, 24.</note> oh that thy words were now written in the Book of my heart! Oh that they were printed in my conſcience! That they were engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with an iron pen, and lead, in the rock of my heart for ever. But alas,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal. 1.6.</note> I am affraid of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of vile affections, which have beſet themſelves round about me; not onely to keep me from holy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pro. 6.25.</note> I luſt not after her beauty in my heart, nor let her take me with her eye-lids; that I am not raviſh'd with one<note n="(l)" place="margin">Can 4.9.</note> of her eyes, and one chain of her neck,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Job 29.22.</note> but to make me mock at her ſear, and not be affrightned, nor turn back from her ſwords, to ſay,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:110756:59"/>among her trumpets, Ha, ha; to ſcorn the thunder of her captains, and their ſhouting! Nay, and as if they themſelves were not enough, they ſay to all temptations,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pro 1.11, 12, Pro. 1.17.</note> Come with us, let us lay wait for blood, let us lurk privily for all the Laws of God that ever come here; Let us ſwallow them up alive, as the grave; and whole, as thoſe that go down to the pit. O my God, are not all thy nets ſpread in vain, in the ſight of ſuch Birds, as my worldly affections: who ſay of heavenly-mindedneſs<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ecc 2.2.</note> that it is mad: and of ſelf-denyal, what doth it? who taunt at my conſcience, ſaying,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Can 5.9.</note> What is thy beloved more than another beloved? O my God! I confeſs it 'tis but juſt on me;<note n="(q)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.2.</note> I have nouriſh'd and brought up theſe children of Belial, and now they rebel againſt me, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering over my heart, (the womb that bare them, and the dugs that gave them ſuck,) ſo that<note n="(r)" place="margin">Ro. 7.15.</note> that which ſhe allows not, ſhe does: that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:110756:60"/>which ſhe would, ſhe does not, and does what ſhe hates. And verily, oh my God, theſe<note n="(s)" place="margin">1 Co 1.27.</note> fooliſh things confound the wiſe within me: theſe weak, confound the things that are mighty!<note n="(t)" place="margin">Eccl 4.1.</note> I have conſidered all the oppreſſions that are done under the Sun; but, oh my God, I know none like thoſe done by my vile af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iſa. 3.15.</note> which beat thy good Teachings to pieces, and grind the faces of my poor convictions, which fence up my way, that I cannot paſs from them, and ſet darkneſs about all my paths, which make me ever and anon grumble.<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſal 73.13.</note> I have cleanſed my heart in vain, and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my hands in innocency! to wit, while they ſay to my graces and comforts,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Jer. 13.18.</note> Humble your ſelves, ſit down, for your principalities ſhall come down, even the crown of your glory! Oh my God, my God! 'tis through theſe that<note n="(z)" place="margin">Jer. 12.2, 3.</note> thou ſo often art near in my mouth, and far from my reins! but oh thou that knoweſt me, ſeeſt me, and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:110756:60"/>my reins; thou knoweſt that I pray thee, for the love of Chriſt, to pull them out like ſheep for the ſlaughter, and prepare them for the day of ſlaughter. For alas! alas!<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 57.20.</note> they are like the troubled ſea, when it cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt up mire and dirt! the winds and the ſeas will obey me, aſſoon as they; and the worſt of it is,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pro 29.12.</note> That my Rulers, my judgement and conſcience, do but too often hearken to their lies, and then all their ſervants, my will, memory, and all other powers are wicked; and ſo wicked, as that if any good ſeed get into me,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Job 14.2.</note> it comes up like a flower, and is cut down; it flees as a ſhadow, and continues not. My God, I fear at my yery heart,<note n="(d)" place="margin">2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 26.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> That (as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi>) I ſhall be a leper to my death, and dwell in a ſeveral houſe, ſever'd from the near acceſs to thee, and thy holineſs, which my heart pants for! becauſe really I am<note n="(e)" place="margin">Job 2.6.</note> in the hand of theſe devils, onely thou ſaveſt my life!
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:110756:61"/>of which it ſelf I am wofully afraid, when many times<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſa. 46.9.</note> they make my very warfare with them to ceaſe; they break my ſpiritual bows, and cut my ſpears in ſunder, and burn the Chariots of God in the fire! Their curſed peace being<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 48, 18.19.</note> all the whiles as a River, and their unrighteouſneſs numerous and boiſterous, as the waves of the ſea! Their ungodly ſeed as the ſand, and their off-ſpring as the gravel thereof. Oh my God, if whoſoever<note n="(h)" place="margin">Luk 14.11.</note> exalts himſelf, ſhall be abaſed, ſure I ſhould hope theſe corrupt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections were to be brought down; for ſure they exalt themſelves above thy own Majeſty. When I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times query with them, methinks the ſum of their anſwer is, what was ſaid of old, Theſe<note n="(i)" place="margin">Iſa. 48.5.</note> and theſe things mine idol hath done, and my graven image, and my molten image hath commanded them; They are ſtedfaſt and unmoveable, alwayes abounding in the works of ſin and vanity. They are<note n="(k)" place="margin">Eph 6.10, 11, 17.</note> ſtrong in the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:110756:61"/>Devil, and the power of his might, putting on his whole armour, that they may be able to ſtand againſt the very ſword of the ſpirit, the Word of God. O my God,<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Ti 3.16.17</note> I find they are notable for doctrine for reproof, for corrections, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in unrighteouſneſs, that the child of diſobedience may be perfect, throughly furniſh'd unto all evil works: they ſubtly<note n="(m)" place="margin">Tit 2.12, 13</note> teach to deny all ſpiritual Godlineſs and Grace, and to live indeed unſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, unrighteouſly, and ungodly in this preſent world, looking for that hope which makes aſham'd! They<note n="(n)" place="margin">Jam 1.21.</note> lay apart all ſpivituality, and godly ſineerity, and receive with proud deſperateneſs the devices of Satan, the leaſt of which, is — enough to damn humane ſouls! To do evil, and to communicate it, they<note n="(o)" place="margin">Heb 13.16.</note> forget not; for with ſuch ſacrifices, the god of this world is well pleaſed: and indeed, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is not ſo<note n="(p)" place="margin">Heb 6.10.</note> unrighteous to them, as to forget their labour of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:110756:62"/>love to him: No, he gives them day by day<note n="(q)" place="margin">Mat 6.</note> their daily bread,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pro 30.8.</note> and feeds them with food con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for them, crying,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Eze. 13.10, 13.</note> Peace, peace, where there is either none, or but ſuch, as thou, oh my God, wilt rent with a ſtormy wind, in thy fury, and conſume with-an over-flowing ſhowre in thine anger! and verily, as theſe vile affections<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 109.18.</note> have cloath'd themſelves with cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as a garment, ſo let it come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their bowels like water, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their bones like oyl. Through them, oh my God, through them, oft have<note n="(u)" place="margin">Jer. 12.7.</note> I forſaken my houſe; ay, my tower, (for ſo is thy Name) I have left my heritage, for ſo is thy Word, and given Chriſt, the dearly beloved of my ſoul, into the hands of his enemies, I have! —<note n="(x)" place="margin">Jer. 11.20.</note> But, oh Lord of Hoſts, that judgeſt righteouſly, that tryeſt the reins and the heart, let me ſee thy vengeance on them; for unto thee have I revealed my cauſe! Amen, oh Jeſu, Amen, for thy Name ſake. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:110756:62"/>
            <head>
               <hi>15.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God againſt ſelf.</head>
            <p>O My God! my ſelf has<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat 18.15, 16, 17.</note> treſpaſs'd againſt me; (and thee too!) I have gone, and told it its fault between it and me! It has not heard me, nor have I gain'd it! I have took with me two, nay three witneſſes, the Three that bear record in heaven, and it has refus'd to hear them! What ſhall I do, but count it a heathen, and a Publican? I profeſs, were not Jeſus a friend<note n="(z)" place="margin">Mat 11.19.</note> to publicans and ſinners, all the manners<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat 12.31.</note> of its ſin and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, could not be forgotten! Is not<note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 22.5.</note> its wickedneſs great, and its iniquities infinite? Oh my God, what ſoul<note n="(c)" place="margin">Job 34.7, 8.</note> is like it, it drinks up ſcorning like water, it goes in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with the workers of iniquity,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 1.1, 2.</note> and walks with wicked luſts! It walks in the counſel of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:110756:63"/>it ſtands in the way of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, it ſits in the ſeat of the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: its delight is great in the law of its members, and in that law doth it meditate day and night!<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pro. 17.1.</note> Better to it is a dry morſel of temporal loſs, and dung, and carnal quietneſs therewith, than a houſe full of ſacrifices to God, with ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to be holy! It<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ecc. 10.20. Mat. 9.20.</note> curſes the King of Heaven in its thought, and thy rich grace in its Bed chamber; and this iſſue of its mad blood, has been more than of Twelve years. Among them that are us'd by the Devil, to devour me, there hath not riſen an agent greater than ſelf; For, oh my God, thou knoweſt, from<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ge. 1.1, 2, 3.</note> the beginning wherein thou createdſt the little of heaven within me, or from the very time wherein thou ſaidſt, Let there be light, and there was light within me, thou knoweſt it has been this my ſelf, which has made me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out form, and (as it were) void: and has put darkneſs on the face of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:110756:63"/>my ſoul, making it, as if the ſpirit of God had never mov'd on the face of it. O Lord, this ſelf is<note n="(h)" place="margin">Jud.</note> the <hi>Sampſon,</hi> which with its Aſſes jaws, has ſlain many thouſands of thy ſpirits motions and convictions in me. It is the <hi>Herod</hi> which ſeeks the life; nay, it is the <hi>Judas</hi> which betrayes, and the <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> which condemns, and the Jew which crucifies Chriſt within me: it is the<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ex. 1.11, 24.</note> 
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> which oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes my graces with Taſk maſters, and makes their lives bitter with hard bondage, in mortar, and in brick, and in all manner of vile ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.<note n="(k)" place="margin">Phil 3.19:</note> The end of which, is deſtruction; the God of which, is the belly; the glory of which, is ſhame; the nature<note n="(l)" place="margin">Jam. 3.15.</note> earthly, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, deviliſh, fooliſh, diſobedient, deceiv'd, ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures, malicious, envious,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Tit 3.3, 4.</note> hateful, and hating the kindneſs and love of God our Saviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man. O God, this ſelf, which<note n="(n)" place="margin">Hoſ 12.1.</note> ſo feeds on the wind, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:110756:64"/>the Eaſt wind, increaſing lies and deſolations, what a<note n="(o)" place="margin">Job. 10.22.</note> land of darkneſs as darkneſs it ſelf, does it make my heart; a place of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, without any order, and where the light is as the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Lord, if I know my heart at all, ſure<note n="(p)" place="margin">Job 42.6.</note> I do abhor this ſelf, and deſire to repent in duſt and aſhes! Though all its pleas and arguments are<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pro. 30.26, 27, 30.</note> a feeble folk, yet make they their houſes ſo, in the rocks of my heart, that I can't for my life get them out: though its luſts have no King reigning in my heart, (as I know of,) yet ſo they go forth all of them by bands, that l'le ſay it, I cannot diſſipate them as I would: for, they are as a lion, the ſtrongeſt among beaſts, and which turns not away for any. O my God! Selfs<note n="(r)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.13, 14.</note> vain oblations, and its incenſe, are an abomination to me! its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed feaſts my ſoul hates, they are a trouble to me, I am weary to bear them!<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pro. 23.3.</note> I am not deſirous of its dainties, I know they are moſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:110756:64"/>deceitful meat. But alas, I too oft eat its<note n="(t)" place="margin">pro. 9.17.</note> bread in ſecret places; and though I know, its wine is a mocker, and its ſtrong drink is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pro 20 1.</note> and whoſoever is deceiv'd thereby, is not wiſe; yet (wo is me)<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pro; 23.31, 32.</note> when it is red, when it gives its colour in the cup, when it moveth it ſelf aright, how do I forget, that at laſt 'twill bite like a ſerpent, and ſting like an adder? Oh Lord my God! When ſhall I be able (as my Love did) to<note n="(y)" place="margin">phil 2, 7, 8.</note> make my ſelf of no repute, and humble and empty my ſelf? Oh that to morrows<note n="(z)" place="margin">Ep. 4.26.</note> Sun might go down upon my wrath againſt ſelf! for, of a truth, in ſelfiſhneſs dwells all the fulneſs of Antichriſt, and that bodily; and 'tis compleat in it, which is<note n="(a)" place="margin">Col 2.9.</note> the head of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's principality and power!<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Th 2.3.</note> Its exhortation is of deceit, unclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and guile. Its luſt oppoſes and<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Th 2, 3.</note> exaltsit ſelf, above all that is called God, or is worſhipped, that it may ſit in the Temple of God,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:110756:65"/>ſhewing it ſelf, that it is God. Its riſe and progreſs is after the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Satan, with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders. Oh my God, if<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Ti 1.51.</note> Chriſt came not into the world to ſave ſelfiſhſinners (of whom I am chief,)<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Co 15.17.</note> my faith is vain; and as I live in, I ſhall dye in my ſins. But through him ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning me, I hope I ſhall (as <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Acts 28.5.</note> ſpake of this viper, though it faſten about me, I hope I ſhall both pluck out my ſelfiſh<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.29, 30</note> eye, and caſt it from me too: chop off my ſelfiſh hands, and caſt them from me alſo; yea, and throw out my ſelfiſh holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelf, unto the dogs. I hope to ſee the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Job 31.22.</note> ar mof all ſelf, fall from its ſhoulder-blade, and broken from the bone; broken in pieces<note n="(i)" place="margin">pſal 89 10.</note> as <hi>Rahab;</hi> and ſerv'd as the <hi>Midianites,</hi> as <hi>Siſera;</hi> as <hi>Jabin,</hi> at the brook of <hi>Kiſon.</hi> If not, piety muſt ſay within me,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Jer. 10.20.</note> my Tabernacles are ſpoil'd my cords are broken: there is none to ſtretch forth my Tent any more, and to ſet up my curtains! and,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:110756:65"/>wo is me, I muſt ſay to the power of godlineſs (if any live in me)<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Ki 20.1.</note> ſet thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt dye, and not live; for ſure I am, ſelfiſhneſs wipes out ſpirituality of obedience, as a man<note n="(m)" place="margin">2 Ki 21.13.</note> wipes out a diſh, wiping it, and turning it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide down: <hi>Nebuchadneuzar</hi> like, it makes a decree, that every power of the powers of the ſoul, that ſhall<note n="(n)" place="margin">Dan 3.5, 6.</note> hear the ſound of its cornets, flutes, and harps, ſhall fall down, and worſhip the golden images that it ſets up; and if any grace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, it muſt be caſt into the midſt of the burning fiery furnace of rage and malice! (like the woman in the Revelation) it is<note n="(o)" place="margin">Rev 18.21.</note> array'd in purple, and ſcarlet-colour'd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, deckt with gold, precious ſtone, and pearl, in its profeſſions, and hath in its hand a golden cup, like a ſacred chalice; but it is full of abominations and filthineſs of its fornications: upon its forehead ſhould be wrote, Myſtery, <hi>Babylon,</hi> the great, the mother of harlots,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:110756:66"/>and abominations of the heart and life! wherefore thou, oh my God, ſend thou the Angel of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Rev 18.21.</note> the mighty Angel indeed; and by his holy ſpirit, let him take up thy word, like a great milſtone, and caſt this <hi>Babylon</hi> into the ſea, and let it be found no more at all in my ſoul, or any of its wayes! As<note n="(q)" place="margin">Exo 15, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s chariots, and his hoſt, were caſt into the ſea, and his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen captains drown'd in the red ſea; ſo let the deeps cover my ſelfiſhneſs, and all its <hi>Aegyptian</hi> crew, let them ſink into the bottom, as a ſtone! Amen, my God, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:110756:66"/>
            <head>17. A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with my Soul, about its eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for Divine Love.</head>
            <p>OH my ſoul, my ſoul!<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pro. 24.24, 25.</note> He that ſaith to the wicked, thou art righteous, him ſhall the people curſe! Shall nations abhor him? I prethee, He that ſaith to his wicked ſelf, Thou art righteous, ſhall not God curſe him too? ſhall not Saints alſo abhor him?<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſal. 39.1.</note> Take heed then to thy wayes, that thou ſin not with thy tongue! Keep the mouth of thy very heart alſo, with a bridle, while thy wicked luſts are before thee.<note n="(t)" place="margin">Job 12.6.</note> The tabernacles of them who rob, and take from Gods promiſes their comforts which they give them not, do proſper for a while; but the wealth of evidences for heaven,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pro 13.11.</note> got by vanity, will be diminiſh'd; when they that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:110756:67"/>them by laborious conſulting the conditions of Goſpel promiſes, ſhall increaſe. The devil's beaſts do not know<note n="(x)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.3.</note> their Owner; nor his Aſſes their Maſter's crib. Without are dogs, which neither ken their being dogs, but dream themſelves God's children; nor believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without divine favour, but conceit them wrapt up in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of it. Thouſands, I am out of doubt, thouſands of Chriſt's<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat 25.33, 37, 44.</note> ſheep, think they are goats; but thouſands of thouſands among Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's goats, think they are ſheep! Many, in whom Chriſt is, think<note n="(z)" place="margin">2 Co 13.5.</note> they are Reprobates; but more, who are Reprobates, think that Chriſt is in them! Oh my ſoul! my ſoul! If I my ſelf,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> or an angel from heaven, do preach to thee any other Goſpel, or ſalvation on any other Terms, than what are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Chriſt's own, hold it accurſed; He that doth<note n="(b)" place="margin">Joh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 21.</note> the truth, cometh to that light, e're his deeds can be made manifeſt, that they are of God.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:110756:67"/>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">pro. 18.17.</note> It being firſt in thy own cauſe, thou ſhouldſt ſeem juſt, God, thy very near Neighbour, will be ſure come ſearch thee out. He leads cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt<note n="(d)" place="margin">Job 12.17.</note> ſelf-counſellers away ſpoil'd, and makes partial Judges of themſelves, fools: and believe me, the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 24.35.</note> heaven of preſumptions ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſhall paſs away, but his works will not paſs away.<note n="(f)" place="margin">pro. 20.6.</note> Moſt men, and eſpecially the worſt, will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim every one his own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but, a faithful friend to God, who canfind for all that? My ſoul, I am ſure thou haſt thoſe within thee, which<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 30.10.</note> ſay to thy Seers, ſee not: and to the Prophets, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie not right things, ſpeak unto us ſmooth things; but for the love of Chriſt, don't let them make<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 28.15.</note> thee make lyes thy refuge, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſalſhood hide thy ſelf. God has written to thee excellent things in counſel and in knowledge,<note n="(i)" place="margin">pro. 22.20, 21.</note> that he might make thee not gueſs, but know, not the probability, but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the words of Truth.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:110756:68"/>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Pro. 3.5, 6.</note> Lean thou not then to thy own underſtanding, but in all thy wayes acknowledge them.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Job 38.2, 3.</note> Don't darken counſel by words without knowledge. Gird up now thy loins, for I will demand of thee, and anſwer thou me! Hath thine eye ſeen God,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Job 42.6, 7.</note> ſo as that thou abhorreſt thy ſelf in duſt and aſhes? Are all thy ſprings in God? and<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſal 121.1, 2</note> doſt thou lift up thy eyes to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hills, for thy ſalvation? Doſt find, that 'tis indeed his<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 104.28, 29.</note> open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hand, that fills thee with good; and 'tis his hiding his face that troubles thee? Art thou ſure of this? Doſt verily believe<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſal. 84.11.</note> that God is the Sun, who gives thee all thy light, without any efficiency of thy lower Moon and Stars? and that he is the onely ſhield in life and death? Is he in good earneſt thy love,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Iſal 119.16.</note> delight, deſire, and joy, and hope? Haſt thou ſaid (as he ſayes) to all other gods, Ye ſhall die? Is<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſal. 97.10.</note> he Lord of lords, God of hoſts, I am that I am, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:110756:68"/>Counſellor and mighty God,<note place="margin">See the whole Law &amp; Goſpel.</note> Holy, Faithful, and True, in thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt reins? Is his Son God-man, crucified under his Fathers wrath, ſatisfactoriouſly, meritoriouſly, and victoriouſly dying, riſing, triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and interceding at his Fathers right hand, thy life, light, bread, raiment, ark, City of Refuge, Prieſt, Prophet, King? Is God the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Joh. 14.18.</note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, thy Enlightner, Quickner, Convincer, Converter, Comforter? Is thy being ſhapen in ſin, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal 51.3, 5.</note> iniquity, ever before thee? Doſt. ſet thy ſecret ſins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, thy<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſal 90.8.</note> hidden ones in the light of thy countenance? Doſt ſmell them ſtink, ready to choak thee, bowing thee, ready to break thee, and killing thee all the day long? Tell me, is the Law the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of thy eyes, and doſt keep it in them? Doſt make it a light to they feet, as well as thy brains? Canſt ſay without lying, thou haſt not a<note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Co 1.9.</note> comfort in all the world, but it ſprings from one or other of the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:110756:69"/>Lord's promiſes? Does his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note n="(j)" place="margin">Iſa. <hi>ult.</hi> 2, 3.</note> word make thee tremble? Doſt live by ſenſe as a horſe; by carnal reaſon, as a man; or by faith as a Chriſtian? Has thy faith any<note n="(z)" place="margin">Acts 26.18.</note> eyes, do they ſee God, heaven, helf, death, and Judgment, every day, every duty, every time, of ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that as real, certain, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputable things?<note n="(a)" place="margin">Jer. 6.10.</note> Has thy faith any ears, can it and does it hear the voice<note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 35.10.</note> of God, in his Word and providential works, that which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural men do no more hear, than ſtocks and ſtones? Don't thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eze 12.2.</note> ears hear the Miniſter ſpeak a great deal, while thy ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ears don't hear God ſpeaking one word of it? Don't lye, but tell me, Haſt ears for God's mouth, as thou haſt for men? Has thy faith<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal 135.</note> a noſe, one that ſmells myrrh, aloes, cinnamon in every Truth, and every good notion, practice, and perſon, together with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in every ſin, though ſweetned with profit, pleaſure, honour, love
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:110756:69"/>of Kings themſelves? What man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal 34 8.</note> of Taſt has thy faith? Does ſecret converſe with God, in bed, at board, on horſeback, in cloſet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Does converſe with thy ſelf, and Chriſt's members (as ſuch)? Do duties of all kinds, ſuch as moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thy own carnal eaſe, and mens carnal peace and fayour? Do theſe taſt indeed, and in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, ſo well<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal 119.103.</note> as honey to thy<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Pe 2.3.</note> palat? Do they affect thee with ſo palpable a pleaſure and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? And laſtly, for God's ſake tell me, what feeling is thy faith of? Can't it let thee go without its robes about thee, but ſtrait feel the ſterming wind of God's wrath, and ſcorching Sun ſhine of his fury? and that as plain, as thy naked body would feel a <hi>December</hi> froſt, or <hi>March</hi> wind, on a hill? Is God thy All, art thou all Gods, and that in ſecret ſober ſadneſs? Canſt vow and proteſt to Father, Son, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rir, that thy heart labours after, and can't, and won't be ſatisfied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out<note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Co 13 14.</note>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:110756:70"/>the grace of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Love of God the Father, and the communion of God the Spirit? If ſo, Go in peace, and the God of peace be with thee. Amen, Lord Jeſus, Amen, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="soliloquy">
            <head>
               <hi>17.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with the World.</head>
            <p>OH World, World!<note n="(i)" place="margin">Joh. 8.48.</note> Say I not well, that thou art a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan,</hi> and haſt a devil? Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is not thy name<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mar 5 9.</note> legion, and art thou not many <hi>Abaddons,</hi> and <hi>Apollyons?</hi> I am ſure thou haſt oft caught Saints themſelves, and they have been<note n="(l)" place="margin">Luk 8. 29, 33.</note> bound with thy chains and fetters, breaking God's holy bonds. And as for unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Swine, into whom thou entreſt, and art not ſoon diſpoſſeſs't, thou hurrieſt them down into the lake, where they are cloathed with fire
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:110756:70"/>and brimſtone! The Devil had leſs ſpecious<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ge 3.</note> apples of old, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude eye with, than thy apples of gold in pictures of ſilver be. If that ſerpent did not eat and feed men with thy duſt, we might triumph over him; oh Serpent, where is thy ſting?<note n="(n)" place="margin">Joh 8.44.</note> oh Devil, where is thy victory? He was a murderer from the beginning, and abode not in the Truth; and waſt not thou a like apoſtate, of whom God ſaid, Thou waſt very good, and by and by<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ge. 1.31. Gen. 3.17.</note> curſed thee! that once bareſt good fruit for the uſe of man's body, now nothing but thorns and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, at leaſt huſks, for ſoul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? I'le ſay't,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Jud 6.</note> Thou kept'ſt not thy firſt eſtate, but art now reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the jud gement of the great Day! And I'le vow my judgement is, that if I don't in the mean time drownthee in the<note n="(q)" place="margin">Rev 12.15.</note> flood of my penitential tears, and burn thee out of my ſoul with the fire of my love and zeal, for a better world, the flood caſt out of thy mouth will
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:110756:71"/>ſwallow me up, and I ſhall find the God of this world a conſuming fire! For if any Devil<note n="(r)" place="margin">Heb 2.15.</note> has the power of death, I dare ſay 'tis the world, to whoſe<note n="(s)" place="margin">Eph 6.12.</note> principalities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, mankind ſo conforms its life! 'Tis the world makes every<note n="(t)" place="margin">Luk 22.3, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> in it, and we betray not Chriſt to our luſts, till that enter into us, and covenant with us: Nor keep we back any thing from him, till this<note n="(u)" place="margin">Act 5.30.</note> Satan fills our hearts, to oppoſe the Holy Ghoſt! Thou, oh world, art the Satan that ſtandeſt ever at our right hands, to reſiſt us! and I vow, I think<note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Ch 10.10.</note> thy little finger thicker, than the loins of all the Devils in hell. If the Saints muſt judge<note n="(y)" place="margin">1 Co 6.2.</note> the world, and the things of the world, I doubt not but they will judge them the worſt enemies, next to luſts after them. If they reſiſt the Devil, he will fly from them; but the earth abideth for ever a Tempter, and its <hi>Herods</hi> which ſeek the life of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, will never be dead. We may
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:110756:71"/>chuſe, whether we will give any place to the Devil, or no; but the world muſt have our backs, on which it makes (but too often) very long furrows: and our bellies, in which it leaves its Idol-gods. Of all its clothes, how few there be that won't be found naked, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered with Chriſt's Garments. I cannot think without horrour, and ſurely did it poyſon as many bellies as ſouls, it would have few to feed. Oh world, world! Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable are thy men, and miſerable the ſervants,<note n="(z)" place="margin">2 Ch 9.7.</note> which ſtand conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually before thee, and hear thy wiſedom, though with that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, of which the world is not worthy. I aſſure<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ecc. 1.8.</note> thee, my eye is ſatisfied with ſeeing thee; and my ear with hearing thee! The Devil brags of thy<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat 4.9.</note> All theſe things; but God calls thy things, things which are not: and if that damn'd Ghoſt did not think my ſoul worth a thouſand of thee, he would ſcarce be ſo buſie with me, to give my
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:110756:72"/>ſoul in exchange for thee. I know by my experience,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Jer. 2.13.</note> thy ciſterns are broken, and can hold no water. My comforts in eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, do tell thy bread and wine, as<note n="(e)" place="margin">See 2 Gen. 45. Mat. 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> his Brethren, It was not you, but God, that ſent me hither. My God knows. I pity as many as gather their grapes from thy thorns; and hold them children, who take their figs from thy thiſtles. Thy<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mar 11.20.</note> fig trees are curſed, and dryed up from the roots. Till Chriſt's bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing return, they are the roots of all evil. I confeſs thou haſt<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luk 12.19.</note> much goods laid up for many years; but hang thee and them too, thou haſt none for eternity.<note n="(h)" place="margin">Job 14.11.</note> As waters fail from the ſea, and the flood dryes up: ſo thy Goods lye down, and rife no more. As oft as I have<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal. 37.25.</note> ſeen the righteous forſaken by thee, I never ſaw them ſo more bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, than<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſal 104.21.</note> the beaſts of the wilderneſs, as to beg bread from thee. A man may poſſeſs all thy things, and yet not ſo much as have
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:110756:72"/>any thing to<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Co 6.10.</note> poſſeſs. One bleſſing of God's makes rich. Ten thouſand of thine can't ſo do! For thee and thy followers are reſerv'd to the Day of Deſtruction; and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, even that which is wanting, cannot be numbred; and that which is, is beſides vexation, no more than vanity. Oh world, world! I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt 'tis Jeſus that muſt feed me with food convenient for me, and cloath me too; thy daily bread without his will ſtarve me.<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mat 13.44, 46, 52.</note> If the Kingdom of heaven be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, thou art a dunghill: If a pearl, thou a cherry-ſtone. Go, get thee and offer thy accurſed things to thy <hi>Achans;</hi> money, and change of rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>Gehezies;</hi> fat cattel to thy <hi>Sauls;</hi> thy <hi>Dalilah</hi>'s to thy <hi>Sampſons;</hi> preferments to thy <hi>Balaams;</hi> and thy preheminence to thy <hi>Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes!</hi> Lay thy ſuares in <hi>Mizpah,</hi> and ſpread nets in <hi>Tabor;</hi> uſe thy laws and menaces, thou ſhalt make no <hi>Demas</hi> of me. I have ſeen thee ſmite the Body of Religion with
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:110756:73"/>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Job 2.7.</note> ſore boils, from the ſole of its feet to thy crown! I have ſeen thee ſhaving many poor Chriſtians, till their ſpiritual ſtrength has gone from them, and they have<note n="(o)" place="margin">Jud. 16, 17.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come weak, and been like other men! When I my ſelf have oft been going about my God's ſervice. Oh world, world! how haſt thou<note n="(p)" place="margin">Nu. 22.22, 24.</note> (as the Angel to <hi>Balaam</hi>) ſtood as an adverſary in my way, againſt me? and made as it were a wall on this ſide, and a wall on that!<note n="(q)" place="margin">Jud. 14.9.</note> How rarely have I found honey in thy carcaſes? How often venom in thy ſweets? God<note n="(r)" place="margin">Job 35.10.</note> deliver me from the ſongs that thou giveſt in the heighth. Better is a Dinner of herbs, where the love of my God is, than all thy ſtalled oxen, and thy love therewith!<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pro. 15.17.</note> Thy goodneſs is as a morning dew, and as an early cloud, it paſſes away: but of thy temptations, one generation paſſes, and another ſtill comes! Thy men are every one a <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres:</hi> Thy things are all <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:110756:73"/>Foxes, with Firebrands to deſtroy piety.</p>
            <p>Yet will I be juſt, oh world! Fle give the Devil his due, I do acknowledge it is my ſin that has made thee thus thy enemy! it is my own fault I am hurt by thee; and therefore ſay I now well to my own heart, my polluted heart, Thou art a <hi>Samarita,</hi> and haſt a Devil.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="soliloquy">
            <head>
               <hi>18.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with the Lord, of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Grace.</head>
            <p>OH my God, my God! I read in thy word that he is<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal 41.1, 2, 3.</note> bleſſed, who conſidereth the poor, that thou wilt deliver him in time of trouble: That thou wilt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve him, and keep him alive, and make him bleſſed on earth! That
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:110756:74"/>thou wilt not deliver him over into the hand of his enemies: That thou wilt ſtrengthen him on the bed of languiſhing, and make his bed in his ſickneſs! Oh my God, how oft has my faith conſidered all my poor diſtreſſed comforts and hopes? How oft has the bleſſing of them, when they have been ready to periſh, come on my faith? Now therefore, oh my God! Deliver my faith in time of trouble, preſerve it and keep it alive; bleſs it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it not over to the hands of its enemies! Strengthen it on the bed of its languiſhment, and make all its bed, on thy promiſes, in its ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! As with a ſword in its bones, my luſts do reproach it, while they daily ſay to it,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal 42.10.</note> Where is now thy God? peace and joy, its<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal 38.11, 12.</note> lovers and friends ſtand aloof from its ſore; and hope and truſt, its ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kinſmen, ſtand afar off. They that ſeek after its life, lay ſnares for it; and they that ſeek its hurt, ſpeak miſchievous things, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:110756:74"/>deceits all the day long! Oh my God, its<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.5.</note> whole head is ſick, its whole heart is faint,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pro. 24.11.</note> it faints in the day of proſperity, its ſtrength is ſo ſmall. It is not with it, as in the dayes of its<note n="(f)" place="margin">Job 4, 5, 6, 19.</note> firſt Love, when the <hi>Secret</hi> of God was upon its Tabernacle; when the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty was yet with it, and its children (of Repentance, Zeal, and Heavenly mindedneſs, &amp;c.) were about it! When it waſh'd its ſteps with butter, and every rock it ſelf pour'd it out rivers of oyl! when its root was ſpread out by the waters of Divine Love, and the dew lay all night on its branches! Now<note n="(g)" place="margin">Jer. 15.9.</note> ſhe that hath born ſeven languiſhes, ſhe has given up the ghoſt, her Sun is gone down, while 'tis yet day. My faith, oh my God, now<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 59.10.</note> gropes for the wall, like the blind; gropes as if it had no eyes, ſtumbles at noon day, as in the night! My hope layes its<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Ki. 23.30.</note> carcaſe in its own grave, &amp; mourns over him, ſaying, Alas my brother!
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:110756:75"/>Oh my God, what ſhall I do! All my graces ſeem to have ſaid to thee as<note n="(k)" place="margin">Exo 10.29.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> We will ſee thy face no more. All their<note n="(l)" place="margin">Gen 48.10.</note> eyes are as <hi>Iſraels,</hi> dim, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee: their ears are ſhortened, that they cannot hear thee: and their arms, that they cannot lay hold on thine. Their leanneſs ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up in them, bears witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.<note n="(m)" place="margin">Job 17.18.</note> Their breath is corrupt, their dayes are extinct, the graves are ready to them. If their Off-ſpring of Duties be multiplied, oh my God,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Job 27.14.</note> it is for the ſword of my vile corruptions;<note n="(o)" place="margin">Jer. 15.3.</note> to their ſword, to ſlay: to their dogs, to tear: to their fowls and beaſts, to devour and deſtroy. Thoſe very duties, that e're while were<note n="(p)" place="margin">Lam 4.5.</note> brought up in ſcarlet, in the very blood of Jeſus, how do they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace even dunghills of rotten, ſtinking Formality, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the ſkin of which being broken, becomes loathſom.<note n="(q)" place="margin">Job 7.5.</note> The hand of faith has offended my luſts,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 18.8, 9.</note> and they
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:110756:75"/>have cut it off! The eye of faith has offended them, and they have pluck'd it out! My hope has offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, and they have made it aſhamed! They have tied milſtones about the necks of all my ſouls graces, and thrown them into the depths of Diſtruſt! But oh my God, my God! though the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Gen 49.23, 24.</note> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers have ſorely grieved them, and ſhot at them, wilt thou yet return their bow to its ſtrength, and ſhall the arms of their hands be made ſtrong, by the hands of the Mighty God of <hi>Jacob?</hi> From whom is the ſhepherd and ſtone of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">Hoſ. 13.9, 14.</note> Though they have deſtroyed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in Thee is their help! Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom thou them from the power of the grave, and redeem them from death! Say to their death, that thou wilt be its plagues; and to their graves, that thou wilt be their deſtruction! So ſhall the very dead praiſe thee, and thoſe that have gone down to the pit, remember thy Name! Nor ſhall my luſts, my<note n="(u)" place="margin">Eccl 9.4.</note>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:110756:76"/>living dogs, be better than my graces, though dead Lions I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem, oh my God,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſal 103.4.</note> Redeem their life from Deſtruction! And, for Chriſt's love,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſal 66.9.</note> hold thou their ſouls (as well as mine) in life! Without thee, oh Jeſus, my life, my food, my raiment, my All; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, what is the life of my grace? it is even a<note n="(z)" place="margin">Jam 4.14.</note> vapour that appears, and but appears for a time, and but a little time, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes away:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Job 24.22.</note> No man is ſure of their life; no, though<note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 2.4.</note> all that a man hath he would give for their life! But, oh by thee, in whom my graces life is hid, may it<note n="(c)" place="margin">Luk 21.28.</note> lift up its head, and may its ſalvation draw nigh! The winds and ſeas obey thee, make thou the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Rev 20.13.</note> ſea of my corruptions to give up its dead! So ſhall my love for thee be ſtronger than death, and my jealouſie<note n="(e)" place="margin">Can 8.7, 8.</note> for thy glory, be cruel to them, as the grave; the coals thereof ſhall be coals of fire, which have a moſt vehement flame.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:110756:76"/>No waters ſhall quench, or floods drown it, though the devil would give all the ſubſtance of this great houſe of the world for it, it ſhould utterly be contemned.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="soliloquy">
            <head>
               <hi>19.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> of vain Thoughts.</head>
            <p>OH my ſoul, my ſoul! Thy thoughts are thy<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen 49.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Reubens,</hi> thy firſt-born, thy might, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of thy ſtrength, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and power, if good: but if unſtable as water, thou canſt not excel. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, That<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Co 13.11.</note> when he was a child, he thought as a child: when a man, he thought as a man. But verily, when I was a child, I thought as a beaſt; when a man, I thought as a child. The mighty God<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal 139.2.</note> underſtands thy thoughts afar off. Oh that thou wouldſt underſtand them better,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:110756:77"/>far and near! For ſolemnly I tell thee, that though<note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb 4.13.</note> all things are naked and open before the God, with whom I have to do, yet are they ſecret ſins which he is ſaid to ſet before him, and hidden ones that he puts in the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſa 9.7.</note> light of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance! Though he be juſtly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note n="(f)" place="margin">Heb 12.23.</note> Judge of all, yet particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly and chiefly he is ſaid, Coming to judge<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ro. 2.16.</note> the ſecrets of men! Of every idle word, an account muſt be given; but<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mat 12.36, 37.</note> of every idle thought, which produces milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them, what account can be given? If (in my ſenſe) I was to be juſtified by my words, I ſhould ſcarce hope well! But alas, if a man offend not<note n="(i)" place="margin">Jam. 3.2, 6, 8.</note> in word, yet if he does in thought, he is no perfect man. Add hereto, that the tongue is no ſuch fire, no ſuch world of iniquity, no ſuch untamable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly member; but the heart is by thouſands, and by ten thouſands, worſe!<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ecc 10.14.</note> Fools indeed cannot rule their words, but the wiſeſt
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:110756:77"/>cannot rule their thoughts. <hi>David</hi> proteſts he hated vain thoughts, but never once boaſts of a conqueſt over them. Beſides, what are our words? They are even a vapour which appear for a little while, and vaniſh away! Evil thoughts are a ſin that dwelleth in us, and tell me, oh my ſoul, oh tell me,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Jer. 4.14.</note> how long ſhall they lodge within thee They have lodged in thee ſo long already, that they have begot a hundred monſters, opinionative, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectional, and practical. I proteſt in God's preſence, to thy face,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ecc 4.1.</note> I have conſidered many of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions that are done under the Sun; and like to that of thine own, by evil thoughts, I know not any. My God alone does know, what I would give, to have my thoughts taught<note n="(n)" place="margin">Tit 2.5.</note> young womens duty, to be diſcreet, chaſt, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers at home; good, obedient to the dictates of my own conſcience, that the word of God might not be blaſphemed: to be ſober, grave,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:110756:78"/>temperate, ſound in faith, in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and patience: to be in behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our as becometh holineſs. But alas, alas!<note n="(o)" place="margin">Job 2.2.</note> their feet abide not in their home; like the devil, they are moſtly going to and fro in earth: they are very<note n="(p)" place="margin">Gen 49.21. Pro. 22 6.</note> 
               <hi>Naphtali</hi>'s, Hinds let looſe, and they love to wander. Let me train them, ever ſo much, in the way wherein they ſhould go;<note place="margin">Pſal 90.9. Mark 14.20.</note> yet inſtantly they will depart from it. If any good be thrown in upon them, yet it paſſes away like a Tale that is told! but rarely falls a ſeed of evil, but it takes root, and bears, ſome thirty, ſome ſixty, ſome a hundred fold. As for all foregoing good inclinations, and purpoſes, they make them as graſs upon<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſal 129.6. Hoſ. 4.11. Rom. 11.8.</note> the houſe tops, which wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before it grows up. In a word, there is much of whoredom, and wine, and new wine in them, which utterly take away the heart, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe a ſpirit of flumber: The form of Godlineſs, they ſometimes feed, even<note n="(r)" place="margin">Luk 15.22, 23.</note> with the fatted calf, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:110756:78"/>cloath with the beſt robe, putting rings on its fingers, and tinkling or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments about its feet too. But for the power of Godlineſs, they ſerve it, as <hi>Samuel</hi> did <hi>Agar,</hi> they hew it in pieces. As for the object of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, the Holy God, ah my ſoul, my ſoul! How abominates he vain thoughts, he removes his way far from them, he<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pro. 5.8. Pro. 4.15. See Pro 6.16, 17, 18</note> will not come nigh the door of their houſe; he, be ſure of it, avoids their manſions, paſſes not by it, turns from it, and paſſes away. Every vain thought is a virtual <hi>Gergeſen,</hi> beſeeching Chriſt to get him gone out of the region of the heart; and ordinarily, a few ſerve to ſend him going. As for the heart it ſelf (the ſubject of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion) vain thoughts, take the Kingdom of Grace out of it, and very reaſon too, in a great meaſure, they drive it from Saints, yea, from men: They make its dwelling with<note n="(t)" place="margin">Dan 4.31, 32. Hoſ. 12, 1.</note> beaſts of the field, they make it to eat the graſs with carnal oxen; with <hi>Ephraim</hi> to feed on the wind,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:110756:79"/>and follow after the Eaſtwind; yea, they ſometimes turn the children<note n="(u)" place="margin">Mat 3.9.</note> of <hi>Abraham</hi> into ſtones, obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and inſenſible. As for acts of Devotion,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Hoſ. 13.3.</note> Prayer, Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Vain thoughts make them, Firſt, to be as the morning cloud, and as the early dew; as the chaff driven with the whirl-wind, out of the floor; and as the ſmoke out of the chimney, which leave no ſign behind them. And Secondly, to be meer<note n="(y)" place="margin">Jud. 12, 13.</note> clouds without water; trees whoſe fruit wither, without fruit, twice dead, pluck'd up by the roots: raging waves of a ſea of hypocriſie, foming out the ſouls ſhame: they make them grievous to us, and odious to God. As for the means of Devotion, holy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation alone, holy conference with Chriſtians, holy uſe of God's Word, and good Books. Oh my ſoul, ſadly doſt thou know, how vain thoughts make one<note n="(z)" place="margin">Rev 3.16.</note> ſpue them out of ones mouth, or at leaſt taſt no more in them, than in the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:110756:79"/>white of eggs. Thou knoweſt, vain thoughts make the heart (like the Leviathans) firm as a ſtone; yea, hard as a piece of the nether mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; and then let God's Books, or his Saints, or both ſay to us (as <hi>Job</hi> to his friends)<note n="(a)" place="margin">Job 27.11.</note> I will teach you by the hand of God, that which is with the Almighty, will I not conceal; Yet they will be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly contemn'd, and be to us Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of no value. As for the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites and Contraries of Devotion, Pride, earthlymindedneſs, Atheiſm it ſelf; vain thoughts are thoſe, which took them out of the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal 22.9, 10. Pſal. 25 13.</note> womb; upon vain thoughts they were caſt from the very breaſts; and vain thoughts were their Gods, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from the belly. Vain thoughts make them to dwell at eaſe, and to lift up their heads above the heads of Humility, Heavenlymindedneſs, and practical piety. All things me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, of every ſort, ſayes to vain thoughts, You are our<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 142.5.</note> refuge, and our hiding-place: You are the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:110756:80"/>hills, whence cometh our help? They will not in truth, my ſoul! they will<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal 3.5. Hoſ. 13.8.</note> not be affraid of ten thouſands of Sermons, which ſet themſelves againſt them: They will lye down, and ſleep, and awake, while vain thoughts ſuſtain them, Sermons, Conferences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would meet every of thy ſins, and rent the caul of their hearts. They would make their ſtrong holds like<note n="(e)" place="margin">Nah 3.12.</note> fig-trees, with the firſt ripe figs; if they were but ſhaken, they would fall. Were it not, that<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal 125.2.</note> as the mountains ſtand round about <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem:</hi> ſo vain thoughts ſtand ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout my corruptions, that the means of Grace can't have full reach of them. Would my God but caſt down my<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Co 10.5. Rev. 18 2. Pſal. 10.4.</note> imaginations, and bring my thoughts into captivity, and the obedience of Jeſus, then ſhould my heart be no longer the habitation of Devils, and the hold of every foul ſpirit, and a cage of every unclean and hateful bird! But hear, oh my ſoul, if God be
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:110756:80"/>in all thy thoughts, vanity and ſin will be in all thy beſt words and deeds! For the love of Chriſt, go cry to thy God, and ſay,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pro, 6.2.</note> Thou art ſnar'd with the thoughts of thy heart! Beg him for Chriſt's ſake, that their root may be dryed up, and they may bear no more fruit; yea, though they ſhould bring forth,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.16.</note> that he would ſtay even the beloved fruit of their womb, and daſh their little ones againſt the ſtones. Now conſider this, oh ye the poor beginnings of grace and comfort within me, leaſt vain thoughts<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal 50.22.</note> tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:110756:81"/>
            <head>
               <hi>20.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> of idle words.</head>
            <p>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen 15.5.</note> LOok now toward Heaven, oh my ſoul, and tell the ſtars, if thou be able to number them! Lift up thine eyes,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Gen 13.14, 16.</note> look abroad from the place where thou art, Northward, and Southward; Eaſtward, and Weſtward. if thou canſt tell the ſtars, and count the duſt of the earth, then may thy<note n="(c)" place="margin">Job 6.25. Mar. 7.18.</note> words alſo be numbred; words, of which there's not one, but is very forcible, whether right or no: for though (but too oft) thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt the words of God of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in one ſenſe, God will never make thine of none effect in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but will by them,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat 12.37.</note> or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, or condemn thee.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Jam 3.10.</note> Out of every of thy ſo many words, a bleſſing or curſe is ſure to proceed;
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:110756:81"/>and wo be to thee, if God make thee an offender, for a word unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of. For as every unſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed tongue, ſo every vain word thereof, is it ſelf a world of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; yea, behold 'tis<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in iniquity, and in ſin doth the heart conceive it. 'Tis by nature a<note n="(g)" place="margin">Eph 2.3.</note> child of wrath, even as other works of diſobedience; 'tis of its<note n="(h)" place="margin">Joh 8.44. Joh. 8.48. Luke 10.17.</note> father the Devil, and the works of its father it will do, damn it ſelf, and its corrupted hearers. Say I not well to every of thy idle words then, Thou art a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and haſt a devil? Devils, without all peradventure, they are; and oh would God, thou couldſt now go, ſay, Lord, theſe devils are ſubject to me in thy Name. If<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Joh 3.8.</note> ſuch as commit ſin, be of the devil, I am certain they are his genuine ſeed and iſſue; for why,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ro. 3.23.</note> ſin dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in them, and they are carnal, ſold under ſin, they lay on thee weights, and make actual ſins eaſily beſet thee. Yea farther, oh my
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:110756:82"/>ſoul, thy idle words have not only ſinned all of them, and come ſhort of the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Ro. 7.13, 14.</note> glory of God; but they have made many to be ſinful through them, who elſe had not known the ſins imparted to them. In a word, idle words (the plague of their plagues is,) they become<note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Jo 2.2.</note> propitiations for ſin, and not for ones own onely, but the whole companies. God's (word is indeed the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſal 119.105. <hi>Read</hi> Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8. Phil. 2.16.</note> light to our feet, and the (due) lanthorn to our paths! But the very truth is, there's (a kind of <hi>ignis fatuus</hi>) a falſe light, ſparkling out of ones own words, which generally does lead our feet, and chalk out our paths. Nor have evil communications a little influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on like manners: every word of ours, is ordinarily a word of life, in a ſenſe, God rarely holding our hearts, when once<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 12.4. Pſal. 2.</note> our lips are our own, and our hands ever break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his bonds aſunder, and caſting his cords behind us, aſſoon as his<note n="(p)" place="margin">Joſh 1.8.</note> Law is departed out of our
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:110756:82"/>mouths. Nor yet, oh my ſoul, mayeſt thou think, that thy tongue or thy words are ſufficient lodgings for Divine Love, they are but for walks, to move and appear in. Thy honour to God, though it be but barren, without the fruit, and the calves of thy lips, yet theſe oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are odious to the very ſoul of God, when they are not offered from out the very ſoul of man. Though ſtinking breath argues rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten lungs, and I am out of doubt, thou art moſt impure, if thy ſpeech be not ſeaſoned with ſalt; yet this I utterly ſet at naught, unleſs thou have<note n="(q)" place="margin">Col 4.6. Mat. 9 5</note> ſalt in thy ſelf alſo. The cleaner thou ſweepeſt before the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mic. 7.5.</note> doors of thy mouth, oh my ſoul, ſweep ſo much the cleaner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the doors of thy heart too, and within its chambers; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, thy<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſal 57.8.</note> tongue will be indeed thy glory, but no more than thy vain glory. Add whereto,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Mar. 3.24, 25.</note> that the Kingdom of God cannot ſtand in humane ſouls, wherein the heart
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:110756:83"/>and tongue ſtand divided againſt each other. The practical impieties of an hypocrite,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Job 29.17.</note> will break his own jaws, and pluck the ſpoils of Grace out of his teeth. If his tongue break not its own word, his hands will. Being evil, he may ſpeak great things, but not good to himſelf, who ſpeaks them, nor very likely to be good to others, coming through ſo polluted lips as his. But, oh my ſoul, <hi>David</hi> ſayes, The words of the Lord are pure words: And his ſon tells thee, The<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſal 12.6.</note> words of the pure are<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pro. 15.26.</note> pleaſant words. Oh count thou them onely pleaſant, which are pure; and them pure, which are godly. Chriſt, who in one ſenſe<note n="(z)" place="margin">Mat 10.19.</note> forbids thee, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other commands thee, to take thought how, and what thou ſhalt ſpeak.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ecc. 5.1.</note> Be not raſh with thy mouth, ſayes <hi>Solomon:</hi> Be<note n="(b)" place="margin">Jam 1.19.</note> ſlow with it, ſayes <hi>James.</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Co 14.19.</note> Five words with underſtanding ones ſelf, and with edifyingneſs to others, are better than ten thouſand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:110756:83"/>the ſame, ſayes <hi>Paul.</hi> The wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of men declares it, That acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable words he did not find, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ecc 12.10.</note> ſeeking them out. The moſt godly of men profeſſes, it coſt him good<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 39.1.</note> heed to keep ſin out of his tongue, and ſometimes 'twas a bridle onely, which could rule it. A bleſſed prophet mentions<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mic 7.5.</note> doors of the mouth, and calls for Porters to keep them to. Were it an eaſie thing, graciouſly to open thoſe doors, Why prayed<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſal. 51.15.</note> 
               <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſo urgently to God, to open his for him? Were it eaſie to keep them duly ſhut; one chapter in St. <hi>James</hi> his Epiſtle, would ſwarm with errors. Though one love pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, 'tis not the natural gift, but the ſupernatural<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pro 22.11.</note> grace of ones lips, for which the King of Heaven will become our friend. In the multitude of words utter'd by the beſt, if there be not a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, yet neither is there any<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pro. 10.19.</note> want of ſin. Thy ſad and woful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience tells thee, Thou art apt to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:110756:84"/>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Exo 23.2.</note> follow thoſe multitudes to do evil. Wherefore do this now, oh my ſoul, and deliver thy ſelf, go humble thy ſelf to God! and give not ſleep to thine eyes,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pro. 6.3, 4, 2</note> or ſlumber to thy eye-lids, till thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd it to him, that thou haſt been ſnar'd with the words of thy mouth, and taken by the words of thy mouth, which had they been ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſound, they had been<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pro 8.11, 19.</note> better than rubies, and their fruit better than gold; yea, fine gold: but being corrupt,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſal 58.4.</note> their poiſon is like the poiſon of a ſerpent; and when beſt painted, they are but ſtinking ſepulchres. Go, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Chriſt of God, to give thee a<note n="(o)" place="margin">Luk 21.15. Rom. 15.6. 1 Cor. 13.1.</note> mouth and wiſedom; wiſedom with my heart, and mouth alſo, to glorifie him all the day long; to make his Word the rule and mold, wherein to caſt mine. Would God, oh my ſoul, the tongue of men and Angels were but one; and the praiſes of God were as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly ſung aloud on earth, as
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:110756:84"/>in heaven! Would God there were no ſuch things, as tongues deviſing<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſal 52.2.</note> miſchiefs, and like ſharp raſors, working deceitfully! Would God there were no tongues of the beaſt, ſave in the mouths of beaſts! and<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſal 49.3.</note> the meditation of humane hearts, were ſo of underſtanding, that the mouth of the whole world would be of wiſedom! Would God iniquitie were more than tongue-ty'd, even rooted out; and the words of men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.7. Mat. 12.34.</note> would become as the words of God, pure words, tried in the furnace purified ſeven times! But ſeeing ſo it (ſadly) is, that out of the abundance of my hearts wickedneſs, my tongue is haſtie to ſpeak. And ſeeing in the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Job 20.12. Pro. 10.14 Mal. 2.7.</note> mouths of the moſt, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſweet, and holineſs bitter as gall: ſeeing the mouths of fools are near deſtroying themſelves, and others too: Seeing God will alſo require his Law at thy mouth; and Chriſt Jeſus owns not thoſe for his, whoſe lips are not as<note n="(s)" place="margin">Can 3.8, 11.</note> thred of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:110756:85"/>ſcarlet, and ſpeech comely; whoſe lips drop not as the honey comb; and under whoſe tongues there's not honey and milk.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Can 5.13.</note> I charge thee, oh my ſoul, before God, and the elect Angels, that thou ſlack not prayer, till thou hear God ſaying to me; All dayes of thy life, I will be with thee, and with thy mouth, and<note n="(t)" place="margin">Exo 4.12.</note> teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="soliloquy">
            <head>
               <hi>21.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> of evil Company.</head>
            <p>CUrſe ill companie, oh my<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal 103.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> ſoul, and all that is within me, curſe its wicked name! Curſe it, oh my ſoul, and forget not all its injuries! which ſets afoot all thy iniquities, and ſtrengthens all thy diſeaſes, which reduces thy ſpiritual life to deſtruction, and crowns thee with the thorns of its loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs!
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:110756:85"/>which fills thy mouth with evil things,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 65.4.</note> &amp; broth of abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things!<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 103.12.</note> As far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo far hath it remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the thoughts of my God, and my Chriſt from me. Even when I remember it,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Job 21.6.</note> I am affraid, and trembling takes hold on me. For it hath caſt down many wounded; yea, many ſtrong in grace, have been ſlain by the wiles of it. Satans agents are ſubtile ſpirits, and his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters a<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal 105.4. Pſal. 76.7. Pſal. 76 1, 2, 3.</note> flaming fire! They, even they are to be feared, and who can ſtand not guiltie, or at leaſt not acceſſary in their ſight? In evil companie. Satan is well known, his name is great in evil companie, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil companie alſo is his tabernacle, and his dwelling-place in evil companies. There breaks he the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the Almightie, the ſhield of Faith, the ſword of the Spirit, and the whole armour of God. Oh my ſoul,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſa. 1.1.</note> 'tis bad walking in the counſel of the ungodly; 'tis worſe ſtanding in the way of ſinners, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:110756:86"/>to ſit in the feat of the ſcornful is worſt of all; unlikely to dwell in God's holy Hill, is that man, in whoſe eyes a vile perſon is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned. Of evil companie,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Job 42.5, 6.</note> I had long heard, by the hearing of the ear; but when my eye ſaw it, and by ſad experience I felt it, I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor'd it, and my ſelf for no more abhorring it, in duſt and aſhes.<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal 149.8.</note> For it binds the motions of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit in chains; and the Dictates of conſcience in fetters of iron: and it works with<note n="(i)" place="margin">2 Th 2.10.</note> ſuch deceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of unrighteouſneſs, in them that periſh by it, that few who<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pro. 2.19.</note> go in unto it, return again, nor take hold ſuch of the paths of life. Thy good companie be to me, but as a very lovely<note n="(l)" place="margin">Eze. 33.32.</note> ſong, of one that hath a pleaſant voice, and can play well upon an inſtrument. Though I hear their words, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do them not, or not as I ought; Yet alas, in evil companie all things are ſaid, and done too, unto edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! They build one up in vanity,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:110756:86"/>and ſinful-mindedneſs; and the<note n="(m)" place="margin">2 Co 10.4, 5.</note> weapons of their warfare, I will ſay it, are (though carnal) yet mightie, through the Devil without, and deviliſh Juſts within, to the pulling down of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt holds of Grace, and caſting down holy apprehenſions, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry divine thing, that exalts it ſelf againſt the works of Satan. True it is, evil companie cannot enjoyn or enforce: yet<note n="(n)" place="margin">Phil 9, 10.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Philemon</hi>) for loves ſake, it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech us to entertain again, thoſe very ſins which we have renounced. Satan cannot force, but ſhrewdly can he tempt; and I much miſtake, if evil companie be not the very brightneſs, and<note n="(o)" place="margin">Heb 1.3, 13. Pro. 2.27.</note> expreſs image of his perſon: Nay, and methinks, I hear the Devil ſaying to all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, Sit you at my right hand, and I will make ſome of your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies my foot ſtool. Deep, oh my ſoul, deep is the ditch, and narrow is the pit of evil company; and it is almoſt<note n="(p)" place="margin">Heb 8 4.</note> impoſſible for thoſe,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:110756:87"/>who are once ſo darkned, as to taſt their helliſh gifts, and be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the damned Ghoſt, who is never more an <hi>Abaddon</hi> and <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luon,</hi> than in evil company, ever again to return ſavingly, to the great Shepherd and Biſhop of ſouls.<note n="(q)" place="margin">Rev 2.13.</note> I know the works of ſuch as dwell in evil companie, even where Satan's ſeat is; they hold faſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's name, and deny not his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. No wonder that <hi>Elihu</hi> cries out,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Job 34.7, 8.</note> What man is like <hi>Job,</hi> if once he goes ſo much, as in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie with workers of iniquitie, and walks with wicked men? <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſaid once to <hi>Abigail,</hi>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">1 Sa. 25.32, 33.</note> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which ſent thee this day to meet me. Bleſſed be thy advice, and bleſſed be thou! But alas! How oft have I ſaid, Curſed be my own ſin in unneceſſary viſits and reſorts! curſed be their advices, and curſed their wayes. It was a true report which I had heard in my minoritie and childhood, of the Acts and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:110756:87"/>madneſs of evil companie; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit,<note n="(t)" place="margin">2 Ch 9.5, 6, 7</note> I believed not their words, who told me thereof, till my eyes had ſeen it. And behold, oh my ſoul, my ſoul, and all that is within me, Behold, the one half was not told me, the ſin of evil companie, and its infectiouſneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the fame thereof! Curſed are their men, and curſed their ſervants, which ſtand continually about them, and hear their folly.<note place="margin">Pſal. 24 7.9.</note> Open the gates of the houſe, and of the heart to evil companie, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt doubt, the Prince of darkneſs ſhall come in; and when he comes, ſhall find or make the heart emptie, ſwept and garniſh'd for his uſe. <hi>Egypt</hi> was no houſe of Bondage, comparable<note n="(u)" place="margin">Exo 20.1.</note> to that of <hi>Egyptian</hi> Companie: nor is ever the Lord's flock ſo carried away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as when they are carried by their own heedleſneſs or worſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Synagogue of Satan: for theſe captivities<note n="(x)" place="margin">Jer. 13.17.</note> weep thou, oh my ſoul, in ſecret places, my
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:110756:88"/>eye ſhall weep ſore, and run down with tears! 'Tis evil companie, oh my ſoul, that deceives its neighbor,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pro 26.19, 18, 25, 26.</note> throws fire-brands, arrows and death, and ſaith, Am not I in ſport. Oh when it ſpeaks fair, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it not, there are ſeven abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations in its heart! Their hate is covered with deceit: may their wickedneſs be ſhewn before the whole Congregation of God. In a worſe ſenſe than <hi>Paul</hi>'s, We are made of the filth of the world, when we have fellowſhip with thoſe who are ſo.<note n="(z)" place="margin">Mat 11.19. 2 Cor. 6.14.</note> Chriſt was a friend indeed, to Publicans and ſinners, and ſo may we. Though he held companie, he held no commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, nor may we. His companie with them, was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them. Wo to us, if our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany-keeping with men evil, be not to make them good, and with a care, they make not us evil. Had the Prince of this world any thing in him to catch him by? nothing at all. Wo then to us, who have ſo
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:110756:88"/>much for him to catch us by, if we make ſo bold as he, in ſome caſes:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.63.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> was companion to all them who feared God, and kept his precepts; in order to which, he took a very good (and it may be the onely) courſe, when he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that he would not know<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal 101.4.</note> a wicked perſon. If I will imitate my God,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 7.11.</note> who is angry with all wicked every day, I muſt be angry every day with my wicked ſelf, and beware of my own companie; and why not as well of all wicked companie.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pro. 15.9.</note> A wicked man is loathſome to God, why ſhould he be lovely to me; or how can he, if I am like God in my affections? Had the Lord Chriſt thought it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for me, to converſe with worldly men, without holding communion with them, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded he would have<note n="(e)" place="margin">Joh. 17.15.</note> prayed the Father, to have taken me out of the world; which ſith he has not, I reſolve to ſojourn (if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence will require me) in
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:110756:89"/>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal 120.5.</note> 
               <hi>Meſech;</hi> and have my habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Kedar:</hi> But to put away<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſal 119.119.</note> all the wicked like droſs, to beware of devils very much, but of men, more, and put a wide difference between men and brethren. And now,<note place="margin">Acts 15 13.</note> oh my ſoul, to confirm thy faith, and animate thy zeal, herein I charge thee before the Trinitie, and the elect Angels, to con well Two Texts, which have flaming ſwords to keep thee out of ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie: The one is <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. The other <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11. All between re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, but theſe repeat thou eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morn, noon, and night. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:110756:89"/>
            <head>
               <hi>22.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God of my Soul.</head>
            <p>LOrd!<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal 119.79. Pſal 139.14.</note> thy hands have made me, and faſhioned me: But nor 1, nor my parents know how! I am fearfully and wonderfully made, in the very<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 40.6.</note> graſs-plat of my fleſh; and even ſuch<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 139.6.</note> knowledge is too wonderful for me, it is high, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attain it. But as for my ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſubſtance,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb 10.34. Heb. 12.9.</note> my better and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during ſubſtance, my ſpirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou art the immediate Father, how that lives, moves, and has its being; what it is, how it-acts, how it lives, man knows not; it<note n="(e)" place="margin">Job 28.21, 23.</note> is hid from the eyes of all living, God onely underſtands the way thereof, and knows the place thereof. Though it dwell in a clod of earth, and a few drops of blood, all the world to it is as nothing, as a
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:110756:90"/>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Iſa. 40.15, 17.</note> drop of a bucket, and the ſmall duſt of the ballance, leſs than nothing and vanity; it takes up the Iſles as a very little thing. Oh my God, my bodie is not ſo little a a thing to the whole world, as the whole world is to my ſoul: fewer ſuch bodies would fill the world, than ſuch worlds would fill my ſoul. Thou haſt but little in ſaying, The world is mine, and the fulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; than thou magnifieſt thy ſelf, when thou ſayeſt,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Eze. 18, 4.</note> All ſouls are mine, ſouls,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Heb 11, 38.</note> of whom the world is not worthy. I have read of the ends of the earth, and<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal. 135.7.</note> I have ſeen an end of all perfection here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. But the capacitie of my ſoul, I find exceeding broad, ſo broad, that nothing leſs than what<note n="(k)" place="margin">Jer. 13.24.</note> ſills Heaven and earth too, can fill it; and if thou, oh my God, wilt fill it when 'tis<note n="(l)" place="margin">Luk. 1.53.</note> hungry, with good things, thou muſt fill it with no worſe, nor leſs, than the fulneſs of God. The<note n="(m)" place="margin">Lu. 58.</note> heles of the earth may contain foxes, and the worlds
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:110756:90"/>neſts may hold unclean birds; nay, each of them poſſibly may ſay,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſal 132.14.</note> This is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell, for I have deſired it! But alas, my ſoul hath not where to lay its head herein! Thy<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 15.1.</note> taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, oh my God, thy holy hill, thy Houſe not made with hands is the leaſt it can dwell in! The whole Earth is not a livelyhood for one ſoul, without thee; nor were Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf tenantable, did not thy preſence make it a Court. Thou didſt once bid man<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ge. 1.28.</note> repleniſh the earth, but never the earth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſh man, whoſe ſoul thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pro. 30.15.</note> and makeſt one of thoſe things which are never ſatisfied; and ſay not 'tis enough, till it has as much more than the World, as the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Gen 3.14.</note> Creator is than the Creation. Oh my God, I find that my ſoul cannot go upon its belly, and eat duſt: if thou thy ſelf wouldſt tell me of the Kingdoms of the earth,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Mat 4.9.</note> All theſe things will I give thee for thy portion, it would utterly be<note n="(t)" place="margin">Can 8.7.</note>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:110756:91"/>contemn'd. I find my ſoul is opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onated, that 'tis a ſubſtance of more value, than many ſparrows, and will not be put off with a this-years neſt, nor with<note n="(u)" place="margin">Luk 12.19.</note> goods laid up for many years neither, no leaſe for leſs than eternity: No inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance beſides an<note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Pe 1.4.</note> incorruptible, and in no place but heaven will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie it, much leſs at all gratifie it. If thou ſhouldſt bid it go ſeek a happineſs, it would return. Lord,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Joh 6.68.</note> to whom ſhall I go, thou haſt the words of eternal life! it would ſay, Lord, every of thy<note n="(z)" place="margin">1 Ti 4.4.</note> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is good, and nothing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed for a ſervant; but I will call none upon earth maſter, while I breath.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Joh 18.36.</note> Had Chriſt's Kingdom been merely of this World, I would never have fought for him ſo much as now I have and will, though I am driven out of the World. But the very truth is,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Joh 3.16.</note> God has ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the World, that I will never love it. I read in thy holy Book of many things loſt; of but two (that
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:110756:91"/>I think of) won. <hi>Solomon</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pro. 11.30. Phil. 3.8.</note> winning of ſouls: St. <hi>Paul,</hi> winning of Chriſt; let me win but thoſe Two, and let <hi>Ziba</hi> take all for me; I cannot be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly anger'd, or pleas'd<note n="(d)" place="margin">Jon. 4.6, 7, 10. Iſa. 5.10</note> with the gourds, which come in a night, and periſh in a night. Oh my God, I find, that whereas Chriſt's ſoul vvas made an offering for ſin, moſt men make their ſouls an offering to ſin: But my ſoul (mindful of its primitive glory, and likeneſs to God) declares its<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ro. 1.18. Job 20.9.</note> Wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſin, offers it ſelf to thee; and reſolves if thou vvilt not, yet ſin ſhall not have it; it vvill not ſerve ſin, or abide by its crib. Nor vvill it humble and<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 113.6.</note> abaſe it ſelf to behold (amorouſly) the things that are on earth. In compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of God, it<note n="(g)" place="margin">Job 42.6.</note> abhors it ſelf; in compariſon of it ſelf, it abhors the gain of the vvhole World. The World, vvhoſe<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mic. 6 10.</note> ſcanty meaſure is an abomination to it; and to all of vvhoſe Treaſures, the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born<note n="(i)" place="margin">Joh. 8.23.</note>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:110756:92"/>Spirit ſaith, not infrequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (as Jeſus to the <hi>Jewes</hi>) Ye are from beneath, I am from above: Ye are of this World, I am not of this World; Adding, that<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat 5.18.</note> Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away; but not a jod or tittle of its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhall paſs away.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Hab. 3.17.</note> Though the fig-tree bloſſom not, nor fruit be in the vines. Though the labour of the Olive fail, and the fields yield no meat: Though the flock be cut off from the fold, and there be no herd in the ſtalls: Though <hi>Moab</hi> reproach, and <hi>Ammon</hi> revile,<note place="margin">Zeph. 2 8.</note> my ſpirit can ſuſtain its infirmity, and through Chriſt proſper too; but without him, enjoyments are torments, and gains loſſes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſurely, oh my God, I may ſay of humane ſouls, That man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the price: and it is ſo far from being<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pro 28.13.</note> found in the land of the living, that with infinite juſtice and prudence we may all cry out, What ſhall we give in exchange?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:110756:92"/>
            <head>
               <hi>23.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God, of Evidences for Heaven.</head>
            <p>OH my God, I cannot but ever and anon break out into ſuch a Quaery of Heaven, as <hi>Abraham</hi> put to thee of <hi>Canaan;</hi> Lord God, How ſhall I know,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ge. 15.8.</note> That I ſhall inherit it. I thank thee, O Lord, I do not yet hear thee ſay of it to me, as of that <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> I have cauſed thee<note n="(b)" place="margin">Deu 34.14.</note> to ſee it with thine eyes, but thou ſhalt not go over thither: But nor yet do I hear thee ſay, (ſo plainly as I would) Fear not, it is my good pleaſure to give thee<note n="(c)" place="margin">Luk 12.33.</note> the Kingdom. Many ſeek to enter in, and are not able: Thouſands not onely ſay and read, but cry Lord, Lord, Open, and yet are ſhut out. Some get ſo far, that they be not
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:110756:93"/>far from<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat 7.22.</note> thy Kingdom, and yet never reach it. Nay, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Kingdom themſelves, (Chriſt tells me)<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat 8.12.</note> are caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to outer darkneſs, the moſt part of them; and if ſo, Lord, what cauſe have I to ſay to my ſoul, as<note n="(f)" place="margin">Rut 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Naomi</hi> to <hi>Ruth,</hi> Shall I not ſeek reſt for thee, that it may be well with thee? Of that ſoul, oh my God, ſo forgetful am I, that oft it checks me (as<note n="(g)" place="margin">Jud 16.13, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Dalilah</hi> her <hi>Sampſon</hi>) Hitherto haſt thou mocked me, and told me lyes; How canſt thou ſay I love thee, and thy heart is not with me. When it reflects on the madneſſes of my heart and life, it fears thou wilt one day ſay of me, as <hi>Achiſh</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Sa. 29.15.</note> of <hi>David,</hi> Have I need of mad men? Shall this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low come into my houſe?<note n="(i)" place="margin">Heb. 4.1.</note> It doth not infrequently alarum me in the being left us of entring into God's reſt, we ſhould come ſhort of it: For<note n="(k)" place="margin">1 Pe 4.12.</note> if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, Where ſhall we appear? <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes, Bleſſed is the man
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:110756:93"/>that fears alwayes. Oh my God, Let me not ſerve thee therefore without fear of my ſelf.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal 118.6.</note> 
               <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſaid, He would not fear what man could do unto him, but ſure he meant of other men: he fear'd his own heart, when he cry'd, Keep, yea,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſa. 119.13 Pro. 29 25.</note> keep back thy ſervant from preſumptuous fins. Indeed the fear of other men, bringeth a ſnare, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes; but the fearleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ones ſelf brings a million. The counſel is divine not to fear o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, who<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat 10.28.</note> can kill our body, and no more. But 'tis alſo as divine, that a man ſhould fear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who is not onely able, but prone by ſin, and by diſobedience, to deſtroy both ſoul and body in hell. Oh my God, Help me to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>Moſes</hi>'s advice,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Deu 4.9. Joh. 13.13.</note> to take heed to my ſelf, and keep my ſoul diligently. I find, That in every Prayer and Conference, wherein I do not ſo do, I muſt cry out to my Lord and Maſter, as <hi>Joſiah</hi> to his ſervants, when ſhot by the Archers,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:110756:94"/>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">2 Ch 35.23.</note> Have me away, for I am ſore wounded, and that in my grace and peace too. As <hi>Martha</hi> of <hi>Lazarus</hi> to Chriſt, I oft ſay of my faith and hope, to my care of my evidences for Heaven. Oh divine eares, hadſt<note n="(q)" place="margin">Joh 11.21.</note> thou been here, my faith and hope had not dyed; and indeed when that is abſent, whatever my labour is in Duties, in the end I muſt ſay, as <hi>Simon</hi> to Jeſus, Maſter,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Luk 5.5.</note> We have toiled all night, and have taken nothing. Wherefore, oh my Bleſſed God and Bounteous, Grant thou, that when thy holy Spirit<note n="(s)" place="margin">Mat 5.41.</note> compells me to go one mile with him, in ſecuring my title to glory, I may go with him twain. Oh let my conſcience be ever tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me, like to what <hi>Michol</hi> told <hi>David,</hi> If thou ſave not<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Sa 19.11.</note> thy life to night, (by enſuring thy evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences,) to morrow thou wilt be ſlain. With ſins, ſorrows, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations. If at any time. I call the proud,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.15.</note> happy (as <hi>Malachi</hi> ſayes;) and ſay in a but ſeeming proſperity
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:110756:94"/>of grace, that I ſhall never be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Oh my God, let thy good Spirit take me off, as the King<note n="(u)" place="margin">2 Ki. 18.19, 20.</note> of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> did <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> What con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is this wherein thou truſteſt? Thou ſayeſt, (but they are but vain words,) I have counſel, and I have ſtrength. O my God, ſay to me of the hoſt of my corruptions, my pride, follie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as once thou didſt to <hi>Gideon!</hi> Ariſe,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Jud 7.5.</note> Get thee down to the hoſt, for I have delivered it into thy hand. Help me, oh Lord, incorruptly to ſay to Jeſus of his Redemption-work,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Rut 2.12.</note> as <hi>Boaz</hi> to <hi>Ruth;</hi> The Lord recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe thy work, and a full reward be given thee of the Lord God of Iſrael, under whoſe wings thou haſt cauſed me truſt; and to vow unto him, as <hi>Ittai</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> As the Lord liveth, and as my Lord Jeſus liveth, (as the living Father liveth, and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus liveth by the Father) ſurely in what place my Lord, (the King of Saints) ſhall be,<note n="(z)" place="margin">2 Sa. 15.21.</note> Whether in death or life, even there will thy
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:110756:95"/>ſervant be. Help me, oh my God to ſet my Jeſus<note n="(a)" place="margin">Can. 8.6.</note> as a ſeal on my heart and arm, with a love ſtrong as death, with jealouſie of all rivals, cruel as the grave. Give me to write on this World, and the glory of it,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan 5.27.</note> TEKEL, Thou are weigh'd in the balances, and are found wanting of any good for my ſoul.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Col. 3.1. Job 23.2.</note> Let my affections be on things above, my comforts in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and my hopes on high. Let me know, oh my God, where I may find thee in all diſtreſſes, and let me come even to thy ſeat! When my heart is overwhelm'd, lead me to the Rock that is higher than I,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſa 61.2. Pſ. 119.139. Job 32.12.</note> Order my ſteps in thy Word, let not any iniquitie have Dominion over me in health, or diſtruſt in ſickneſs: in both let me eſteem thy Word above my neceſſary food or phyſick! And ſo, oh my God, of my evidences for heaven,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat 10.20.</note> it ſhall not be I my ſelf that ſpeak, but thy Spirit in me. Amen, my God, Amen and Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="soliloquy">
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:110756:95"/>
            <head>Whiles this Piece lay at the Preſs, it pleaſed GOD to viſit the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> with the <hi>Small Pox,</hi> and gave him a Recovery full of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; of which (upon his Friends requeſt) he hath annexed his <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>24.</hi> A <hi>Soliloquy</hi> with God, after Recovery from a Sore Diſeaſe.</head>
            <p>OH my God I am ſure I can ſay,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat 25.36.</note> I was ſick, and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:110756:96"/>thou viſiteſt me! Oh that in the Day of Judgement, thou maiſt ſay likewiſe to me, I was ſick, and thou viſitedſt me! I read of thy own people, that once<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 42.25.</note> they had a fire about them, yet they knew it not; nay, and it burn'd them, yet they laid it not to heart! Sure I am, I had my Diſeaſe about me, and I knew it not: nay, and it brake out on me, and never entred into my heart what it was, till by thy providence 'twas made known to me. So unable was I to do thy work;<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 103.3.</note> , to heal all my diſeaſes my ſelf, that in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſenſe, and another too, I might and ſtill muſt ſay,<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Co 4.4.</note> I know nothing of my ſelf.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 39.12.</note> When with this rebuke thou didſt correct me, for my iniquities, thou madeſt my beautie to conſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way like a moth, but in ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, did thy grace correct me, that I may uſe the great Apoſtle's words;<note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Co 1.27.</note> When I was weak, then was I ſtrong; for all the while<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſal. 73.26.</note> my fleſh fail'd, my heart never fail'd:
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:110756:96"/>and whiles my diſeaſe chang'd, and my ſores much deſtroy'd my ſkin.<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.5.</note> neither was my head ſick, nor my heart faint.<note n="(i)" place="margin">Job 7.5.4.</note> When my fleſh was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ath'd with ſcabs and botches, my ſkin broken, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come loathſome through thy grace, oh my God, I was not full of toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſings to and fro, I had yet then it ſelf<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pro 24.33, 34.</note> a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, a little folding of the hands to ſleep, till my eaſe came to me, as one that travell'd, and my victorie of my Diſeaſe, as an armed man. My bodie did, (oh may my ſoul ſo too)<note n="(l)" place="margin">Jam. 1.21.</note> quickly lay aſide all the filthineſs and ſuperfluitie of its naughtineſs; and by thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, receive that temper which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved my ſoul from leaving it! it ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly laid aſide every weight,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Heb 12.1.</note> and the Diſeaſe which did ſo eaſily beſet it, by thy commiſſion; all my diſtempers<note n="(n)" place="margin">2 Sa. 18.7.</note> dealt as gently with me, as if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, oh my God, hadſt charg'd them of me, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> charg'd <hi>Joab, Abiſhai,</hi> and <hi>Ittai,</hi>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:110756:97"/>of <hi>Abſolon;</hi> Deal gently with the young man; and at thy word of command, they departed from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me evil; oh may they now do me good! For<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.67.</note> before I was afflicted, I went aſtray, and ſo I am afraid to my heart, I ſhall after it.<note n="(p)" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.15.</note> If in my affliction, I ſought thee early, what I ſhall do out of it, I am very jealous: for thouſands call to thee,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſal 41.3.</note> to make all their bed in their ſickneſs, who commune not with thee, on bed or up, in their health. Thouſands cry to Chriſt Jeſus, to<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 2.17.</note> take their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and bear their ſickneſs, who yet ſacrifice their ſtrength and health to the Prince of Devils, and live not to God. But in thee, oh my God, do I truſt for good! I will not ſuſpect that thou haſt ſo cur'd my bodie, as to have kill'd my ſoul: this were to ſay to the whole Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, (as <hi>Job</hi> to his Friends,<note place="margin">Job 13.14.</note>) Ye are all Phyſicians of no value. There is, oh my God,<note n="(s)" place="margin">Jer. 8.22.</note> aBa Im in <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> and a Phyſician there, for
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:110756:97"/>healthy as well as ſick Iſraelites. Oh let me have both! for Lord, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to him himſelf, who ſaid, That<note n="(t)" place="margin">Mat 9.12.</note> the whole need not a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, but the ſick: if I don't need thee now I am whole, as much as when I was ſick. When I was ſick did I ſay? Alas, alas! Though my ſcabs be prettie well off, and ſores competently up agen, I am (thou knoweſt oh Lord) nothing but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wounds, and bruiſes,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iſa. 1.9. Can. 2.5.</note> and putrifying ſores! I am ſtill ſick of all things, ſave of love to thee; nor do I find, that this rod of thy late correction, hath driven ſo far from me, as I could wiſh.<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pro 22.15.</note> Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the ſeminary of all Diſeaſes, that not only is in, but bound up in my my heart pit. Bleſſed God, I am not of them, on whom thy rod is not! but ſith thy<note n="(y)" place="margin">Job 21.9.</note> rod with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy reproof, gives no wiſedom that I know of, oh lend me the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or I loſe the comfort of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer! If thou doſt not ſpare thy<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pro. 29.15.</note> rod, yet if thou denyeſt thy
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:110756:98"/>counſel, I ſhall conclude my ſelf a hated ſon, or a reprobate<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 8. Pa. 48.10.</note> ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard. I read, affliction is called a fornace; Lord, if it be ſo, heat it as hot as<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dan 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi>'s, ſeven times hotter, and in with me into it, rather than let the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Jer. 6.29.</note> bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows be burnt, the lead conſum'd of the fire, the founder melt in vain, and my wickedneſs not be pluck'd away. Help me, oh my God, that I deſpiſe not, or miſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this, or any of thy<note n="(d)" place="margin">Job 5.17.</note> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements; for that is a meer kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat 23.37.</note> of thy prophets, and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them that are ſent to me! yea, 'tis a very ſaying, Who is the Lord, that I ſhould fear him? All the ſickneſſes and the ſorrows, that I improve not to<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat 3 2, 8.</note> repentance and amendment of life, methinks in my reflections they bring me down, this thy diſmal word, of old pronounc'd,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Gen 3.16.</note> I will greatly multiply thy ſorrow! But verily, oh my God, when one of thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifements<note n="(h)" place="margin">Deu 32.30.</note> chaſes a thouſand of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:110756:98"/>my corruptions; and two puts ten thouſand to flight: There be three that bear record in heaven, how unfeignedly I conclude, That affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with<note n="(i)" place="margin">Jo. 6.6.</note> contentment is great gain! I cannot ſay of all my Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Job: 17.12.</note> as Chriſt of the Elect, Thoſe that thou gaveſt me, I have ſaved, and none is loſt; but yet ſure I am, ſome of my afflictions there be, which when they have done all, cannot ſay,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Luk. 17.10.</note> We are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervants; for of one and another, oh my God! thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, that<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mat 1.20.</note> that which has been conceiv'd in them, has been of the Holy Ghoſt. My perils by ſea, that made me cry,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat 8.25, 27 1 Cor. 3.21.</note> Lord ſave, or I periſh, through thy grace, made the wind and ſeas of my own tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous affections, more obedient to my conſcience, ever ſince, in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberacies. But alas, of any man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, I cannot glory in my ſelf!<note n="(o)" place="margin">Gen 47.9.</note> Few and evil (like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s dayes) have all my improves of thy corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions been; and though in this
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:110756:99"/>ſickneſs I hear a voice<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note> of Chriſt, Come and follow me; and in the many ſingular providentials of it, I ſee a bleſſed plentie of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes too, I fear I ſhall not<note n="(q)" place="margin">Joh. 6.12.</note> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up the fragments, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be loſt. But, oh thou that haſt ſweetly<note n="(r)" place="margin">Phil 3.21.</note> changed, and art yet changing my vile bodie. Let this ſickneſs be unto the death of many a corruption, and let my ſoul be<note n="(s)" place="margin">2 Co 3.18.</note> changed into the image of thy Son from glorie to glorie. Let not my pride, and ſecuritie, and forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my God, like <hi>Lazarus,</hi> come out of their<note n="(t)" place="margin">Joh. 11.39.</note> graves, after they have been in for a few daies, and have ſtunk in my noſthrils! If thy Spirit help me not ſtrongly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in thee, though all my ſins were dead,<note place="margin">Joh. 11.25. Joh. 10.10,</note> yet they would live, they would ſtand up from the dead, and unbelief would give them life! Unbelief, which when it comes, it comes that all ſins may have life, and that they may have it more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly. How oft, oh my God,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:110756:99"/>do I methinks hear this unbelief ſay of all ſins (as Chriſt of him whom he loved) Our friends ſleep, but I go that I may awake them out of ſleep. Through faith,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Heb 11.33.</note> oh Lord, give me to ſubdue King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; yea, the world of oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to my dutie, in improving this my Recoverie! I mean, this thy<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eze. 37.6.</note> laying ſinews upon me, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging fleſh upon me, covering me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with ſkin, and putting (as it were) a new life into me. Forbid good God, that the ſhew of my<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 3.9.</note> countenance ſhould cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and<note n="(z)" place="margin">Job. 31.38. Pro. 17.8. Pro. 17.17.</note> the furrows thereof complain of me, for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſs to thee. Let this thy gift of my new life, be to me (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaies all gifts are) a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtone! Whither ſoever it turns, let it proſper to my faith, hope, and charitie. He tells me, a friend loves atall times; I know no ſuch friend but thy ſelf; nor any brother born for adverſitie, but the Saints elder
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:110756:100"/>Brother. He ſaies, the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pro. 18.14.</note> Spirit will bear infirmities. But oh, if he mean not by the upholding of thy Spirit, my experience contradicts him! Wherefore thou, oh Triune God, art my God, and early will I ſeek thee, becauſe thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is my life, and<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 63.3. Pſal. 54 6.</note> better than my life, I will bleſs thee while I live, and I will lift up my hands in thy Name, I will ſacrifice unto thee.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 4.12.</note> Thy Vows are upon me, oh God, and I will render prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes!<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.11.</note> Thy word will I hide in my heart, that I may not ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee! Every day will<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 145.2.</note> I bleſs thee, and I will praiſe thy Name for ever and ever.<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal 146.2.</note> While I live will I praiſe the Lord, I will ſing praiſes to my God, while I have any being! and in this <hi>Quaery</hi> I will live and dye.<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſal 116.12</note> What ſhall I render to the Lord for all his benefits? Oh my God, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word of the Devil I will veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, and all that I have will I give
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:110756:100"/>thee for my life: Nay, and I will uſe his Words alſo to thee, of all that ever I ſhall have in this world, or in the world to come.<note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. 4.9.</note> All theſe things will I give thee. Amen, my God, Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
